<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the antient lavves of great Britaine. George Saltern</title>
            <author>Salteren, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851730</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851730</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17021</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17021)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1005:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the antient lavves of great Britaine. George Saltern</title>
                  <author>Salteren, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for Iohn Iaggard, and are to bee solde at his shop in Fleetestreete, at the signe of the hand and Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-L⁴ M² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: De antiquis Britanniæ legibus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain --  Antiquities --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17021:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17021:1"/>
            <p>OF THE ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENT LAWES OF <hi>great Britaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seruato Ius, metue Mortalis Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>George Saltern.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Iaggard,</hi> and are to bee ſolde at his Shop in Fleeteſtreete, at the Signe of the hand and Starre. 1605.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17021:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17021:2"/>
            <head>De Antiquis Britanniae <hi>Legibus.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all actions, in euerie</hi> election, in euery counſell and deliberation, it is to bee held for a certaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted principle, that, One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges Godly, juſt, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie are to be done, &amp; that with due inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diuine aſſiſtance, without the which nothing can be done. So the firſt conſideration ought to bee of the end, the ſecond of the meanes, the third of the effectuall working power, which cannot be hindred, which is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſpirit of God all ſufficient.<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1</note> By this wee may ſee how that ground is to be vnderſtood, which ſome haue taken, namely that in al inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations there ought to be vrgent neceſsitie, or euident vtilitie. A ground which if it had bin v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely as it was firſt propoſed by a <hi>Pagan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vlpianus.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:3"/>
I would ſay that it were altogether vnperfect &amp; defectiue, ſeeing the conſideration of Godlines &amp; juſtice, is quite omitted; but ſeeing the ſame is now taken and preſſed by Chriſtians, I will deſire them to admit a Chriſtian expoſition, &amp; to ſay that Religion, Piety &amp; Iuſtice, doe carry the waight of neceſsity and vtility, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is Godly and juſt, the ſame is neceſſarie &amp; proffitable, according to the ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> Godlyneſſe is proffitable to all things &amp; hath the promiſes of this life and of the life to come. And againe whatſoeuer is not Godly &amp; juſt, the ſame is not to be done whatſoeuer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie or vtilitie may ſeeme to bee in it: as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.37</note> He that loueth Sonne or daughter more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, is not worthy of me. And ſo that grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is much more perfect &amp; abſolute which out of a <hi>Pagan,</hi> is thus expreſſed:</p>
               <q>Seruato ius et metue mortalis Deum.</q>
               <p>How Godly and juſt a thing it is to eſtabliſh a perfect Vnitie in theſe Kingdomes, for the confirmation of an euerlaſting peace betweene them, and by conſequence thereof, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and propagation of Gods truth and his Goſpell, in a former treatiſe I haue ſhewed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the beſt of my vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:3"/>Now I take in hand to ſpeake of our aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Lawes, and God is the beginning and end of my worke. The thing it ſelfe is no leſſe fit and neceſſarie for this time to be knowne, then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and difficult to expound. For whether we conſider our Statutes enacted ſince the <hi>Norman,</hi> wee ſhall finde them grounded vpon moſte juſt and prudent jntentions: or the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of our Actes made by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> we ſhal ſee them ful of Godly &amp; deuout admonitions, or the ſecret footeſteps of the auncient Britiſh conſtitutions, appering yet in the bodie of our common Lawes, the principles thereof will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be the verie Lawes of the eternal God, written in the two immortal tables of nature &amp; Scripture. The reaſon heereof ſurbordinate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the gracious ordinance of the Almightye, was either the bleſſed diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Princes, whoſe matches for Godlineſſe and vertue no countrie but the Cradle of our Sauiour could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer affoord (as our eyes now doe witnes,) or the natiue inclination of our people moſt apt to be led by piety and deuotion, as the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of examples doe prooue: or the religious &amp; happie counſell of <hi>Elutherius</hi> to <hi>Lucius</hi> King of Brittain, who hauing publikely receaued in his
<pb facs="tcp:17021:4"/>
kingdome the faith &amp; Goſpel of our Lord, and ſtudying to amend his Lawes then vnperfect, ſent vnto the ſaid <hi>Elutherius</hi> for a Coppy of the <hi>Romane</hi> Lawes. The Chriſtian Biſhop made ſuch an anſwere to the firſt Chriſtian King, as betweene two ſuch perſons ought to paſſe; As the moſt high God anſwereth his moſt faithful ſeruant.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo. 25.40</hi> Inter Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges S<hi rend="sup">ti</hi>. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. Archaion. Fox ex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquo codice See alſo Monemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. Bed. Li. <hi>1.</hi> Pontic. vir.</note> Make al thinges according to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne &amp;c. So writeth this good Biſhop. <hi>Petistis a nobis leges Romanas et Caeſaris vobis tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti, quibus in regno Britanniae vti voluistis: Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Romanas et Caeſaris ſemper reprobare poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Legem Dei nequaquam. Suſcepistis enim nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per miſeratione diuina, in regno Britanniae Legem et fidem Chriſti. Habetis penes vos in Regno v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramque paginam. Ex illis dei gratia, per conſilium regni veſtri ſume legem, et per illam Dei patientia, vestrum rege Britanniae regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vicarius vero Dei estis in Regno iuxta Prophetam regem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note>
                  <hi>Domini eſt terra, et plenitudo eius, orbis terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum et vniuerſi qui inhabitant in eo. Et rurſum iuxta prophetam Regem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Dilexisti iuſtitiam, et o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti iniquitatem, Propterea vuxit te Deus tuus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo Laetitiae, prae confortibus tuis. Et rurſus iuxta propheta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 72</note> 
                  <hi>Deus iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regi da, et iuſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filio regis. Non enim Iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neque iuſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb facs="tcp:17021:4"/>
Caeſaris Filij enim Regis gentes Chriſtiane et po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli regni ſunt qui ſub vestra protectione, et pace et regno degunt et conſiſtunt iuxta Euangelium, quemadmodum gallina congregat pullos ſub alis, &amp;c. Gentes vero regni, pulli vestri ſunt, quos diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos debe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is in vnum ad concordiam, et pacem, et ad fidem, et ad legem Chriſti, et ad ſanctam eccleſiam congregare. &amp;c.</hi> This counſell I ſay might bee the reaſon, and by all likelyhood was the reaſon that our common lawes are ſo much grounded vppon the lawe of God, which I am the rather mooued to beleeue, for that I ſee our learned Iudge Mr. <hi>Bracton</hi> ſo oftentimes inculcating the ſentence of this Epiſtle, and namely that <hi>Rex est vicarius Dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 1. C. 2.</note> and deriuing ſuch excellent concluſions from it,<note place="margin">Lib. 3. C. 9</note> as of Godlines in the Prince and of dutie and obedience in the ſubiect &amp;c. And the effect heereof hath been that which is written in the Scriptures: <hi>Verbum Dei manet in aeternum.</hi> Theſe lawes ſaith the learned Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> haue been in the times of the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, Romaines, Saxons, Danes</hi> and <hi>Normanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Forteſcue de laudibus Legum.</note> and if they were not the beſt Lawes, ſome of thoſe Kings (eſpecially the <hi>Romans</hi>) would haue changed them. Of theſe thinges therfore I haue to ſpeake matters farre aboue the mediocritie
<pb facs="tcp:17021:5"/>
of my knowledge: but that I may the better do it, I humbly beſeech thee O true light of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie! to whome all ages and times are preſent, to reuiue the memorie of thy glory eſtabliſhed by thee in our auncient Lawes, lighten my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, confirme my judgement, &amp; leade mee in the wayes of truth and juſtice, ſeeing that without thee neither any man can doe, nor I can ſpeake any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 2.</head>
               <p>ORder of learning, and of the ſaid Epiſtle doth require, that before I enter into the diſcourſe of our auncient Britaine lawes, I ſpeake ſomewhat concerning the <hi>Romane</hi> Lawes, that it may appeare that neither the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend <hi>Elutherius</hi> was deceiued in judgement, nor the Godly <hi>Lucius</hi> in his choiſe, nor the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Forteſcue</hi> in his teſtimony: but that our ſaid auncient Lawes were, indeed, as well as by the <hi>Romanes</hi> owne confeſſion (in that they did not change them) better then their owne. I ſpeake as a Chriſtian, for aſmuch as <hi>Brittain</hi> receaued the Lawes of Chriſt before it knew the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Rome;</hi> but becauſe I wold be loath to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:5"/>
I will remit the reader that is deſirous to know, what may be ſaid of the Authors &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the firſt <hi>Romane</hi> Lawes:<note place="margin">Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei. L. <hi>3</hi> Weſembech prefat in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſag. Riuall. in hiſt. Iur. de Iuſtiniano.</note> to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Augustin</hi> and of theſe now extant to <hi>VVeſembechius Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallius, Procopius,</hi> and others: And for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and groundes, I will referre them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the particulars of the twelue tables yet in parte remayning, and to meaſure and examine the rules of the Inſtitutes by the wordes of the Authors, out of which they ſeeme to bee taken: <hi>Ariſtotle, Tully, Iſidorus. &amp;c.</hi> and both by the Scriptures: a woorke worthy the vacation of a learned man. But for the Lawes of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> my principall intention before I come to ſpeak of them, I will intreate a little leaue to ſpeake ſomewhat firſt of lawe in generall, and ſecondly of the auncient inhabitantes of this Ile. For by knowing what they were, wee ſhall the better knowe their Lawes and manners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 3.</head>
               <p>THe Lawe by <hi>Aristotle</hi> is called a couenant of the ſocietie of men.<note place="margin">Polit. <hi>1.</hi> De Leg.</note> By <hi>Tully</hi> the reaſon and minde of God diſcerning juſt and vniuſt: If we joyne theſe two and call it the couenant
<pb facs="tcp:17021:6"/>
made by God with the ſocietie of men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne reaſon,<note place="margin">Ex. 34.27 &amp; 20. v. 5.6 Deut. 5.2</note> diſcerning juſt &amp; vniuſt: it agreeth with the words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and will be as I take it a perfect definition.</p>
               <p>The end as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith is manifeſt, <hi>Ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ciuium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Leg. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ciuitatumque incolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nitatem vitamque omnium quietam et beatam.</hi> Agreeing alſo with <hi>Moſes,</hi> if <hi>Salus et Incolumitas et Beatitudo,</hi> bee taken for all the bleſsing of this life, and the life to come. Lawes are called Diuine or Humane. The deuine Lawes are thoſe which God imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately made, firſt written in nature, ſecondlye deſcribed in the ten commaundements, &amp; the Scriptures. Humane Lawes are Lawes deriued out of the diuine Lawes by applycation of the generall commaundements, Firſt to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal parties <hi>viz.</hi> to God, to the common eſtate, and to priuate men according to the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the twelue Tables:<note place="margin">Auſon.</note> ſecondlye to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar circumſtances of Perſons, thinges, actions, times, places, Penalties and ſuch like, as the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes are deuided.</p>
               <p>Heerehence followeth a concluſion obſerued alſo by <hi>Tully;</hi> that if a Law be made contayning any thing contrary to the Lawe of God, it is not to be called a Lawe, (though all the world in a
<pb facs="tcp:17021:6"/>
ioynt Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t confirme it. For neither is it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued out of the general precepts, nor partaketh of the common definition, ſeeing it is not a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God, but a confederacy againſt God.</p>
               <p>The property and effect of the Lawe is firſt to make a diſtinction of juſt from vniuſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlye to commaund and forbid. Thirdlye to punniſh and rewarde. Theſe thinges are performed originallye and gennerally by the Lawe of God, and ſecondarily and particularly by the Lawe of men. The quallities of a true Lawe are reckoned vp by <hi>Iſidorus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Eſſe debet Lex Honeſta, Iuſta, poſſibilis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Decret. Part. <hi>1</hi> Weſemb.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecundum naturam et conſuetudinem, Loco et tempori conueniens, neceſſaria vel vtilis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſta. &amp;c.</hi> A Lawe muſt bee honeſt, juſt, poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, agreeable to nature and cuſtome, to time and place, neceſſarie or profitable and manifeſt: &amp; of this proceedeth another ground alſo, <hi>jus nemini violare vel ignorare Licet. Item lex obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat ad ſcientiam, ad obedientiam, ad paenam.</hi> The Lawe bindeth to knowledge, obedience, &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: no man may breake it, no man may be ignorant of it, and that which <hi>Iſidore,</hi> ſaith, when Lawes are made, no Man may judge of them but according to them. The exact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb facs="tcp:17021:7"/>
of the Lawe is called Iuſtice,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Ethic.</hi>
                  </note> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Lawe vppon conſideration of circumſtances, is called equitie, the contraries to the law are jniurie, jniuſtice, jniquity, wrong, force, fraud &amp; ſuch like. Whatſoeuer is ſaid of the Law of God abſolutely, may proportional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be applyed to the Lawe of men. The end of the Lawe of God is al happines. That happines which is the end of Humane Lawes, conſiſteth chieflie in the conſeruation of Religion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.85.</note> Peace, and Iuſtice, all which thinges are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> vnder the name of peace, which alſo he maketh the finall end of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God.<note place="margin">De Ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Dei. li. <hi>19</hi>
                  </note> The matters which the Lawes doe handle, are chiefly perſons, things, places, times, contracts, offences and actions. In this Iland, perſons appointed ſpecially for the procurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, are the Archbiſhops, Biſhops &amp; Miniſters; for the preſeruation of Peace are the Nobilitie, Sheriffes, and Iuſtices of peace. For the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, the Iudges, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors and Officers of Lawe. And the King hath from God ſupreame authoritie ouer all, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſentence, <hi>Rex eſt Vicarius Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other diſtinctions there be of Perſons, but it is not my intention to ſpeake of euery diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:7"/>
but onely ſo much as may ſerue to giue light to the Diſcourſe intended.</p>
               <p>Things alſo haue many diuiſions, whereof I meane to touch but one, which is that ſome may paſſe by courſe of inheritance, as Landes and tenements: ſome cannot, as Chattelles.</p>
               <p>Of places, ſome haue ſacred priuiledge, as Temples, repreſenting God by his woord. The Kinges preſence and Iudiciall Courtes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting God in power and Iuſtice; others are ordinarie and common, and of them ſome are publique: as Markettes, Wayes: Some priuate, as Houſes, Shoppes. &amp;c. Times are likewiſe diuided into ſacred and common, the Day, the night, and ſuch like diuiſions. Contracts haue manifold Diſtinctions, which ſee in <hi>Bracton.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bracto. L. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Crimes, are either againſt Religion, Peace, or Iuſtice, and againe are conſidered as publike offences, &amp; ſo <hi>Rex pro pace ſequi debet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bracton.</note> in which all the Pleas of the Crowne are contayned, or as ſome particular perſon is intereſſed, who is to ſue accordingly. Againe, they may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued ciuilly or criminally. Laſtly, actions are diſtinguiſhed for the moſte parte according to the things which they demaund, or the perſons plaintifes or defendants, or the Courts wherin,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:8"/>
or the times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. In actions, are theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes: Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, or Citations, triall, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and execution: Theſe points as fitter to be ſought in other places, &amp; as to learned men, and as my ſelfe not halfe learned, I doe briefely paſſe ouer, haſting to ſpeake ſomewhat of the Inhabitants of this Lande, and ſo to that which I intend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 4.</head>
               <p>AMongſt the ſeueral opinions that haue bin conceiued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the firſt poſſeſſors of this Iſle, I cannot ſee any more conſonant to diuinity, to reaſon, and the teſtimonies of beſt approoued Antiquaries, then that which maintaineth the Nations of <hi>Brittaine</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of <hi>Gomer</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> whoſe children, after the diuiſion of tongues, at <hi>Babel,</hi> ſpred throughout al <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; ſo repleniſhed this Iſland, <hi>De tractu Armoricano (vt fertur) in Britannia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduecti</hi> ſaith the venerable Bede.<note place="margin">Bed. Hiſt. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And to ſay that any multitude of <hi>Chams</hi> poſterity ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued heere to inhabit, is in my vnderſtanding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the grounds aforeſaid. For firſt there is no probabilitie to maintaine that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or families, deſcended of one ſonne: as of
<pb facs="tcp:17021:8"/>
                  <hi>Iaphet,</hi> were mixed with the Children of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For then how ſhould the accompliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Prophecye be obſerued, which God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced before by the mouth of <hi>Noah?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> that <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> ſhould be a ſeruant both to <hi>Sem</hi> &amp; <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and that <hi>Iaphet</hi> ſhould dwel in the tents of <hi>Sem:</hi> Secondly, it is euident, that almightie God gaue to euery famely of the Sonnes of <hi>Noah</hi> his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Language, &amp; his ſeuerall Country, by theſe reaſons: <hi>viz.</hi> by the ſuruay of all Nations the Sonnes of <hi>Iaphet, Madai</hi> the <hi>Medes; Iauan</hi> the <hi>Ionians; Tubal</hi> the <hi>Iberians; Meſchech,</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouites; Gomer,</hi> the <hi>Cymbri; Ashkenas,</hi> the <hi>Tuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cones.</hi> The Sonnes of <hi>Cham, Cush,</hi> the <hi>Aethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Miſraim</hi> the <hi>Aegiptians, Canaan</hi> the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites:</hi> the Sonnes of <hi>Sem, Ashur, Ela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Apachshad, Lud</hi> and <hi>Aram,</hi> euerie one had his language and his Countrie, and as I take it the contrarie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewed.</p>
               <p>And this is confirmed by the expreſſe words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or rather of God himſelfe, the trueſt Author: where hauing named,<note place="margin">Gen. 10.</note> firſt the Sonnes of <hi>Iaphet</hi> by themſelues, <hi>Gomer</hi> and the reſt, hee addeth this concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Of theſe, were the Iles of the <hi>Gentles</hi> diuided, in their Landes euery man after his tongue, and after their families, in their
<pb facs="tcp:17021:9"/>
nations. So hauing reckoned the Children of <hi>Cham,</hi> euerie one by name, hee addeth the like concluſion:<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> Theſe are (ſaith hee) the Sonnes of <hi>Cham,</hi> according to their families, according to their tongues in their Countries, &amp; in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The like concluſion he maketh after the ennumeration of the Sonnes of <hi>Sem.</hi> And the ſame point is prooued by the Hiſtorie of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 12</note> where he is commaunded to goe from his Country, from his Kindred, &amp; from his Fathers houſe:<note place="margin">Deut. 32.8.</note> and againe by the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other places of Scripture. So as it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by the wordes of the Scripture, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the languages were confounded,<note place="margin">Vid. Auguſt Lib. <hi>16.</hi> de Ciuit. Dei.</note> yet the ſeuerall kindreds, and families deſcended from the Sonnes of <hi>Noah,</hi> were not confounded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but that euerie familie had his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar tongue and country, and were ſeuered from other Families. And it is alſo likely, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer their ſpeeches were confounded, and their families deuided: yet the Sonnes of <hi>Iaphet</hi> had amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues more intelligence one of an others language, then they had of the languages vſed by the natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deſcended of <hi>Cham,</hi> or <hi>Sem.</hi> For wee ſee the <hi>Aſsirians, Perſians, Syrians,</hi> and <hi>Hebrewes</hi> deſcended of <hi>Sem,</hi> had more ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:17021:9"/>
of ſpeech, and writing among themſelues, then they had with any the nations of <hi>Europe.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Aegiptians, Aethiopians, Libians,</hi> &amp; other deſcended of <hi>Cham;</hi> which vicinityes (as I may call it) of ſpeech, being greater in thoſe ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal times, then now it is, cauſed thoſe families that had beſt intelligence one with another to ſorte themſelues together, in places of neerer neighbour-hood, And thereof it came, that the Children of <hi>Sem</hi> remained in <hi>Aſia,</hi> The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Cham</hi> went into <hi>Africa,</hi> &amp; the children of <hi>Iaphet</hi> went northward into <hi>Europa;</hi> as wee ſee the <hi>Moſcouits,</hi> the <hi>Thracians, Ionians</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians,</hi> the Sonnes of <hi>Iaphet</hi> to be round about vs. Of all which premiſſes reſteth this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that all the inhabitants of <hi>Britaine</hi> are deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from ſome one of <hi>Iaphets</hi> Children.</p>
               <p>Other teſtimonies of the Scriptures incline the ſame way,<note place="margin">Ezech. 38.</note> for <hi>Gomer</hi> and <hi>Togarmath</hi> his ſonne are called the ſides of the North; &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men doe agree,<note place="margin">Camden.</note> that the auncient <hi>Kimbri</hi> or <hi>Gomeri,</hi> the Sonnes of <hi>Gomer</hi> did reigne farre &amp; wide in one neighbor Countries;<note place="margin">Sir Iohn Priſe.</note> and the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Brittaines</hi> doe yet call their countrie <hi>Gim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri.</hi> So that in Diuinitie and reaſon we cannot chooſe but acknowledge our ſelues to be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:17021:10"/>
of the ſame ſtocke, namelye the <hi>Gimbri</hi> of <hi>Gomer,</hi> &amp; likewiſe the <hi>Saxons</hi> &amp; <hi>Danes</hi> of <hi>Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenas,</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> If <hi>Iberi</hi> of <hi>Tuball,</hi> and al of <hi>Iaphet:</hi> But if the <hi>Scotti</hi> wil confeſſe themſelues to be <hi>Getae,</hi> according to the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the moſt learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden,</hi> then are they deſcended from <hi>Gether,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sem,</hi> as <hi>Melanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſheweth.<note place="margin">Beda. Li. <hi>1.</hi> Mel. Ch. <hi>1.</hi> Camden. Folidor vir. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Sir Iohn Priſe.</note> And to theſe opinions the reaſons and authorities of beſt antiquaries doe concur, which he that deſireth to ſee, may peruſe them in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden</hi> and others, neither will I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate any mans opinion, (though to me ſomewhat improbable) in deriuing vs from the <hi>Troianes,</hi> ſo as hee deriue the <hi>Troianes</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, from <hi>Ashkenas</hi> which will come to the ſame effect. Taking therefore the former opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or howſoeuer it be, the inhabitants of this Iſle being by all mens confeſsion, a moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent nation of the poſteritie of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and who (as <hi>Gildas</hi> ſeemeth to ſay) had at the firſt the knowledge of God;<note place="margin">Gildas cited by Polidor.</note> it ſtandeth with reaſon, &amp; with beſt warrant of authoritie, to thinke they were gouerned by ſuch Lawes, and inſtitutions deriued from the Principles of the firſt age, that is from the Lawe of God written in nature, as moſt of the auncient nations did imbrace, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17021:10"/>
verye neere to thoſe which the Godly <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> in whoſe tents God perſwadeth <hi>Iaphet</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, deliuered to his Children; of which I intend to perticulate ſome heerafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 5.</head>
               <p>I Haue ſpoken of the Lawe in generall, and of the firſt inhabitants of this Land; and I haue to ſpeake ſomwhat in generall of the Lawes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by our Chriſtian King <hi>Lucius</hi> vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of <hi>Elutherius</hi> Letters, meaning to deſcend in to perticularities, by eaſie paces and degrees.</p>
               <p>But in ſetting down things of ſo ancient time, whereof remaine but fewe Hiſtoryes, through the rage of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and other ſauadge ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, the ſcourges of this kingdom, in her god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infancye; Leſt I ſhould ſeeme to ſpeake too much of mine owne braine; I would intreat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery prudent, ſober, &amp; Chriſtian Politician, firſt to examine the contents, and ſentences of that godly Epiſtle, &amp; ſecondly to conſider his owne minde, and to vnfolde his ſecret vnderſtanding, what he himſelfe would haue done, &amp; what he would think fit to doe, it he had bene then King <hi>Lucius,</hi> or of counſell with him, hauing receiued ſuch a Letter as before is ſet downe?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:11"/>Touching the Epiſtle it ſelfe, it contayneth an anſwer to the demaund of King <hi>Lucius.</hi> The demaund was, to haue the Lawes of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Caeſar.</hi> The anſwer conſiſteth of two partes; a Rejection, We may (ſaith he) alwaies reproue the Lawes of <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but not the Lawes of God. And an exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to take a Lawe for his Kingdome, out of the Lawe of God. This he inforceth, with diuers reaſons and ſentences of Scripture, which with an admirable conſent, do euery one proue each other, and euery one the ſeuerall partes of the anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt you are Gods Vicar, therfore you muſt rule by Gods Law &amp; not by <hi>Caeſars.</hi> The earth is the Lords, therfore it muſt be ruled by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of the Lord, and not by <hi>Caeſars.</hi> God hath annoynted you to be King, <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted you, therefore &amp;c. O God, giue thy judgements to the King, therefore not <hi>Caeſars:</hi> what then would you doe, being a godly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, vpon the reading of ſuch a Letter? Let our moſt Chriſtian King S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> giue vs counſel; who in his Lawes,<note place="margin">La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. Arch.</note> taking the words of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his ground-worke, ſaith thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex autem, quia vicarius ſummi regis est, ad hoc eſt constitutus, vt regnum terrenum, &amp; populum
<pb facs="tcp:17021:11"/>
Domini, &amp; ſuper omnia ſancta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tucatur Eccleſiam eius, &amp; regat, &amp; ab iniurioſis defendat, &amp; male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficos ab ea euellat.</hi> And a little after, he ſheweth how this may be done: <hi>Debet vero Rex Deum timere ſuper omnia, &amp; diligere, &amp; mandata eius per totum Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum ſeruare. Debet etiam, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Eccleſiam regni ſui, cum omni integritate, &amp; libertate iuxta conſtitutiones patrum, &amp; predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum ſeruare, fouere, manutenere, regere, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra inimicos defendere: ita vt Deus prae caeteris honoretur, &amp; prae oculis ſemper habeatur. Debet etiam bonas eges, &amp; conſuctu dines approbatas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigere, prauas autem delere omnes, &amp; a regno de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere. Debet iudicium rectum in regno facere, &amp; iuſtitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per conſilium procerum regni ſui tenere.</hi> Thus ſaith St <hi>Edward,</hi> but if the counſell of ſo excellent a King doe not reſolue you, yet in the mouth of two witneſſes let euery word be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and peruſe the wordes of a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Counſellor and Lawyer, I ſay <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. who there ſpeaketh to the ſame effect,<note place="margin">Bracton.</note> grounding likewiſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame golden foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. <hi>Rex est Dei Miniſter &amp; Vicarius; Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas itaque ſua iuris est non iniuriae, Potestas autem iniuriae Diaboli eſt, non Dei,</hi> and ſo after to the like effect, as S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward</hi> had ſpoken.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:12"/>I think therefore, there is no man but wil ſay that King <hi>Lucius</hi> did accordingly: namely, that according to the contents and directions recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, he did call a Counſel or Parlament, a thing vſed in thoſe times, as I will ſhewe heer-after: He did ſuruay the State and Lawes of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; that which was agreeable to Gods holy worde he did confirme, and that which wanted he did newly enact. Reaſons perſwading me to thinke, that King <hi>Lucius</hi> did ſo, are theſe: Firſt his Godly zeale, which would neuer haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to <hi>Rome</hi> for Lawes, without a great deſire, to haue the beſt lawes to gouern his Kingdome; and to my vnderſtanding it is ſenceles and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, to ſay that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had receiued an anſwer ſo good &amp; agreeable to his deſire, that he would leaue it vnfollowed and vnperformed. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid that he wanted will, ſeeing he ſent for Lawes, nor that he wanted time, opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, power, or conſent of his Nobles or people, ſeeing all, or the moſt part, yea the <hi>Druidae</hi> and <hi>Flamnies</hi> embraced Chriſtian religion together with him,<note place="margin">Beda, ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus virum. Polidor Monemuth.</note> as our Hiſtories teſtifie; and he ruled the <hi>Britains</hi> long time after in flouriſhing peace and tranquility. Againe, that he retayned ſome of the former Lawes; the common opinion of
<pb facs="tcp:17021:12"/>
thoſe auncient Chriſtians of the Primitiue age, perſwadeth me, wherof I will ſpeake more, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I come to K. <hi>Lucius</hi> his lawes. Yet by the way one text will I cite, out of <hi>Iunius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iun. in epiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ola, ad Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Moſ.</note> who ſaith that as long as Heathen Emperors, &amp; Kings held the raines of gouernment, the Chriſtians gaue not their mindes to diſpute the queſtion of the vſe and authoritie of <hi>Moſes</hi> Lawes; but when the State changed, &amp; Chriſtian Emperors were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, then thoſe moſt ſapient &amp; orthodoxall Fathers, ſeeing it moſt expedient to turne about this world, without any greater noiſe, forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the troubles of ſecular affayres, left the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, both of making lawes &amp; giuing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the ordinarie Magiſtrates; but if any were inſtituted <hi>Contra Recta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rationem, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in natura et ſcriptura explicauitus De;</hi> againſt right &amp; good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which God in nature &amp; Scripture hath deſcribed, that either with gentle &amp; calme admonitions they procured to be amended, or patiently ſuffred, if it were incurable, leaſt the whole common good (which <hi>Augustin</hi> before called Peace) ſhould be ſtirred in hope of ſome particular; For, that many times the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of men bringeth to paſſe, whiles they ſeek to cure one euill, they ſhake and weaken the
<pb facs="tcp:17021:13"/>
publike eſtate. In which wordes beſides the point in hand, is much to be obſerued, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to bee in the Lawe againſt reaſon: which is the vniuerſall Maxim, the maine foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and as I may call it, the abridgement of all our common Lawe, which heere you ſee to be the rule of thoſe auncient fathers, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to haue been expreſſed by the Diuine wiſdome of God in nature and Scripture. This is it whereby all our queſtions, and controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, all our arguments and iudgements, all our Statutes and cuſtomes, are ruled and ouerruled, enlarged and corrected.</p>
               <p>But againe to our purpoſe, St. <hi>Augustin</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much to the ſame effect.<note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>19</hi> C. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Haec ergo caelestis Ciuitas dum peregrinatur in terra &amp;c.</hi> This hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly City whiles it is in Pilgrimage vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, calleth Citizens out of all nations; and in all tongues, aſſembleth a Pilgrime ſocietie; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the manifold diuerſities of manners, Lawes and cuſtomes, not repealing or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of thoſe thinges, whereby the terrene peace (ſo I reade) is eyther procured, or preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but rather keeping and following that, which although it be diuerſe in diuerſe nations, yet ſtill is intended to one and the ſame end of
<pb facs="tcp:17021:13"/>
Terrene Peace, ſo long as it is no hindrance of the Religion, whereby the onely ſupreme and true God is taught to bee worſhiped. To the ſame effect he ſpeaketh againe in the nineteene Chapter of the ſame booke.</p>
               <p>Theſe authorities therfore leade me to beleeue, that King <hi>Lucius</hi> retayned ſuch of the auncient inſtitutions, as were not <hi>Contra rectam rationem</hi> (as <hi>Iunius</hi> ſaith) <hi>quam in natura et ſcriptura ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicauit Deus.</hi> And that he did take ſome part of his Lawes, out of the Scriptures, is proued by the teſtimonies of our Chronicles, compared with the words of the moſt Godly &amp; religious King <hi>Alfred</hi> in his Lawes.<note place="margin">Lamb. Arc. Higde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. virun: Galf. Mon.</note> The Chronicles ſay that <hi>Gildas</hi> the auncient Godly <hi>Brittaine</hi> Prieſt who liued not much more, then 500. yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, and not much aboue 300. after <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> tranſlated the Britiſh Lawes into Latine, &amp; afterward <hi>Alfred</hi> the Godly <hi>Saxone</hi> Prince, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the ſame into <hi>Saxon;</hi> and ſo continued them to poſteritie.<note place="margin">Lamb. Ar.</note> 
                  <hi>Alfred</hi> in the entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his Lawes, ſetting firſt the ten Commaundements, and many judiciall Lawes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and laſt the Apoſtolicall Epiſtle directed to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> mencioned in the Actes,<note place="margin">Actes. 15</note> which hee concludeth with theſe wordes vſed in ſome tranſlations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:14"/>That you will not haue done your ſelues, do not vnto others; windeth vp all with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: By this one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement (ſaith he) it is euident inough, that Law and right is to bee giuen to all men equally. Neither ſhall we need of any other, whatſoeuer iudiciall booke, onely let this bee infixed in the minde of him that ſitteth as judge vpon others, that he giue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſentence of other men, then he wold haue to be giuen in his owne cauſe.</p>
               <p>But in the propagatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goſpel (ſaith King <hi>Alfred</hi>) when many men beleeued in the word of God, then many <hi>Synodes</hi> were gathered; and alſo in England, the Biſhoppes &amp; other the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt men aſſembled, who being taught by the mildenes of Chriſt, did ſet vpon euerie firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender a pecuniarie paine, the leuying whereof they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the Magiſtrates. &amp;c. And a little after.<note place="margin">Lamb. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaion.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe I Alfred the King haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together and committed to writing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſpeaking alſo of the lawes of later time, he addeth that there were many thinges, alſo which he thought fit to be obſerued in the acts of <hi>Ina, Offa</hi> &amp; <hi>Ethelbert:</hi> but the former words are plainely ſpoken of the Lawes heere eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vpon the firſt receiuing of the Goſpell by
<pb facs="tcp:17021:14"/>
King <hi>Lucius,</hi> &amp; doe fully prooue that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>herius</hi> was followed, but with the mercifulnes &amp; mildehartenes of our Lord chriſt after the <hi>Saxon</hi> phraſe, and the <hi>Sinodes</hi> which <hi>Alfred</hi> ſpeaketh of in the firſt arriual of the Goſpell, were the Parlaments of <hi>Lucius,</hi> whoſe courſe that it was ſuch as I haue ſaid, I pray you ſee alſo by that which followeth, wherein I wil firſt ſpeake of the remnants of the Lawes of nature, ſecondly of the auncient Brittiſh Lawes made before and by <hi>Lucius,</hi> and laſtlye of thoſe that followed vntil the Norman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 6.</head>
               <p>IT is manifeſt in Hiſtories, both ſacred &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, that the moſte auncient Nations had their Kings or Princes, their Prieſts, their Elders or Senators, and their Dukes or Captaines:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic.</hi> 3. <hi>Leg.</hi> Gen. 18. Iob. 12. Pſa. 105.21</note> and this ſeemeth to bee according to the Lawe of God &amp; Nature, &amp; it is ſeene in the Hiſtories of <hi>Egipt, Iudaea, Madian, Arabia, Greece, Italy.</hi> So <hi>Caeſar</hi> found in <hi>Britaine, Reges, Druidas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> 
                  <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, et Nobiles Duces.</hi> For it is to bee noted, that where hee nameth the foure Kinges of <hi>Kent,</hi> he ſheweth withal, that they were all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibellan,</hi> and calleth <hi>Cing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>torix Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb facs="tcp:17021:15"/>
ducem,</hi> which proueth that he ment by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> (as commonly the <hi>Romanes</hi> vnderſtood) men of nobilitie, power &amp; gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though it were but in one City, as he ſaith of <hi>Immanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entius</hi> in London, who perhaps might then be a Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the city,<note place="margin">Proaem. L. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> as the Lord Maior is now, and ſo dooth <hi>Polidor</hi> take it, ſaying that they were foure Princes, ſuch as wee now call Earles or Dukes.</p>
               <p>It is prooued alſo amongſt Antiquaries, that the famous <hi>Belinus</hi> and <hi>Brennus,</hi> &amp; it is not hard to be proued that <hi>Mulmutius</hi> and others were Kings of this Iland,<note place="margin">Bed. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Beda</hi> the moſt faithfull Hiſtorian ſaith literally, that before the yere ſix hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred after Chriſt in <hi>Britaine, Seruaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vt cuu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Reges, Sacerdotes, priuati, et optimates ſuum quique ordinem.</hi> But of the auncient Kings as likewiſe of their Elders or Nobles, I finde two ſorts, the one fatherly, and the other tirannical. the firſt hauing and maintaining the authority of the firſt age,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei Lib</hi> 15. <hi>et</hi> 19. <hi>Ariſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit.</hi> Gen. 17.29 Gen. 27.29 et 49.10.</note> wherein <hi>Patres familias regebant,</hi> the Fathers of the greateſt families which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained others, were Kings, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Sem</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> and <hi>Aſſur</hi> his Sonne: the Fathers of inferior families, yet populous and great, were Elders, or Princes; as <hi>Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:15"/>
Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Iob.</hi> Such there were in <hi>Britain,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> &amp; <hi>Gildas</hi> doe ſhew. The ſecond ſorte obtained their authoritie by warre, violence or Rebellion, as before the floud, <hi>Cain</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Nimrod, Eſau</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>And of this ſort there was alſo in <hi>Britaine</hi> whoſe times <hi>Gildas</hi> calleth <hi>vetuſtos immanium Tyrannos annos.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gildas in Epiſtola.</note> But as I take it the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Nobilitie of <hi>Britaine</hi> had a name ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much as Elders or Senators, as they had in other Countries before mencioned. Of that ſignification there is a name in many auncient recordes to be found, a name of auncient nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which importeth in ſignification an Elder, which I take it was the name of that firſt &amp; moſt auncient Britiſh Noble man. The name it ſelfe is Thane, and I finde this name vſed for a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man in this Iland in <hi>Denmake</hi> &amp; in <hi>Ireland.</hi> It muſt needes be a name proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the nations that raygned in theſe Countries, but neither the <hi>Romans,</hi> nor <hi>Saxons,</hi> nor the <hi>Danes,</hi> nor the <hi>Irish,</hi> can giue a reaſon whereby to claime it as a woord of theirs: Onely the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> haue a word moſt neere, both in letter, ſignification &amp; vſe. For where the <hi>Danes</hi> call a Lord or a Noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thane, as the <hi>Britains</hi> did,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:16"/>
and where the Iriſh call him Tane, which by reaſon of his Elderſhip is next to ſucceede in ſome Lordſhippe: yet neither of them giue a reaſon for it: onely the <hi>Britaines</hi> vſe the woord <hi>Heane,</hi> or <hi>Hane,</hi> to ſignifie an Elder; which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to the word <hi>Thane,</hi> as I ſaid both in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſignification &amp; vſe. And to verifie the ſaying that all thinges make an Harmonious conſent to truth, The Hiſtorie teſtifieth, that the <hi>Saxons</hi> immediately after their comming into this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, called their Nobles by a name of the ſame ſignification <hi>viz.</hi> Earles or eldermen, a name of Nobilitie vnknowne in their owne Countrie; where (as I take it) they are called <hi>Graues</hi> or <hi>Greues,</hi> ſignifying a gouernor which name alſo they brought hither, and it remaineth in ſome vſe to this day: But the name of Elder they lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the <hi>Britaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And heereunto agreeth the text extant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Lawes of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward. Sicut modo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur Greue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamb. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaion</note> 
                  <hi>qui ſuper alios perfecturas habent, ita apud Anglos antiquitus vocabantur Ealder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, quaſi ſeniores, non propter ſenectutem, cum quidam adoleſcentes eſſent, ſed propter ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Et ſimiliter olim apud Britones temporibus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in regno iſto Britanniae vocabantur Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natores
<pb facs="tcp:17021:16"/>
qui poſtea temporibus Saxonum vocaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Aldermani.</hi> And to ſay that the <hi>Britaines</hi> vſed the name of <hi>Senator,</hi> or borrowed this name of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> is very publikely, for they liued in perpetuall hatred and hoſtility with them, as they ſhewed vpon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l occaſions, &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not their lawes, nor inſtitutions in any thing: but by conſtraint, ſeeing them to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes, Idolaters, oppreſſors of their liberty, and perſecutors of their Religion.</p>
               <p>Neither doth <hi>Beda</hi> nor any other Hiſtorian ſpeake of any Lawes made in <hi>Britaine</hi> by the <hi>Romanes,</hi> nor of any iudgements by them exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: but of thoſe (if they be to be called iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) whereby <hi>Albanus</hi> &amp; other holy Martirs were moſte cruelly put to death. Therefore I conclude that the <hi>Britaines</hi> tooke this name &amp; other inſtitutions, not of them, but either of the auncient ſtatutes of nature, or of the latter reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itution by the Goſpell. Theſe Nobles therefore together with the Prieſts &amp; other ſelected com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, made the common Counſel of this Iland whereof <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſpeaketh, and which at this day is called the Parlament, and in the moſte of our Hiſtories called <hi>conſilium Sapientum.</hi> In the Lawes of <hi>Edward</hi> before the conqueſt, &amp; in the
<pb facs="tcp:17021:17"/>
Lawes of King <hi>Ina</hi> made about the yeare 720. after our Lord Chriſt, there is mencion of theis Parlament conſiſting of theſe degrees of men.</p>
               <p>An hundred yeares before that, we read that <hi>Bertha</hi> the Chriſtian Queene of <hi>Kent</hi> procured judgements to be eſtabliſhed <hi>Cum conſilio ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bed. Lib. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> that is by the Parlament, where alſo the venerable <hi>Bede</hi> ſpeaketh warily, ſaying that it was after the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the <hi>Romans,</hi> but not ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was after the <hi>Romane</hi> manner. An hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before that againe in the time of <hi>Arthur</hi> the warrior, we reade of Parlaments, and the moſte learned King <hi>Alfred</hi> in his lawes ſaith plainely, that vpon the propagation of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Lamb. Ar.</note> 
                  <hi>Nonnulli tam in Anglia quam in alijs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionibus Epiſcoporum aliorumque clariſsimorum ſapientum conuentus agebantur,</hi> which could not bee after the <hi>Romane</hi> faſhion: &amp; whoſoeuer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the circumſtances of the matter, he ſhal perceiue it euidently to bee ſpoken of the time of King <hi>Lucius</hi> (as I ſaid before) for in his time being peaceable, the Goſpell was firſt publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued,<note place="margin">Beda Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid. Monu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Polidor.</note> and after his death, this Kingdome continually laboured with inteſtiue warres, in which it was almoſt impoſsible to gather coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and to eſtabliſh Lawes and gouernment as
<pb facs="tcp:17021:17"/>
he ſpeaketh. And as it was in this ſouth part of <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſo was it likewiſe in the north, as appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by their Chronicles. They had Kinges, Prieſtes, Nobles, and Parlaments, agreeable to the forme of gouernment of the moſte auncient Kingdomes, and to the Lawes of God written in Nature &amp; Scripture: &amp; in this forme conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the eſtate of both the Kingdomes of great <hi>Britaine</hi> euen to this day. And thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the principall perſons, whereof the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our ſtate did and doth conſiſt: the next thing to be conſidered is, of thinges according to the proceedings of the inſtitutes, but becauſe nothing can bee without a place, and wee ſhall haue better occaſion to ſpeake of the diuiſion, property and dominion of things heereafter, I will therefore vnder correction, intreate now ſomewhat of the auncient diuiſion of this Iland, the common place &amp; ſubiect of our diſcourſe, and of the iudgements therein aunciently vſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 7.</head>
               <p>IT is thought by ſome, that this Iland before the comming of the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Camden.</note> was rude and barbarous: &amp; by other, that King <hi>Alfred</hi> was the diuider of this Iland into ſuch Shires and porci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:17021:18"/>
(for ſo the word importeth) as at this day we ſee. But theſe two opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be true ingene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not yeeld; for if I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſtories, it wil eaſily appeare that this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, before <hi>Alfreds</hi> time, deuided almoſt into as many parts, &amp; in like manner by the ſeueral fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies or nations of au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient <hi>Britaines,</hi> which are thus reckoned by <hi>Hooker</hi> in his 2. Booke of the deſcription of <hi>England.</hi> Cap. 4. viz. <hi>Nonantae Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonae Dannonij, Gadeni, Ottadeni, Epdij, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones, Carmonacae, Careni, Cornubij, Decantae, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, Mertae, Macomagi, Venicontes, Texati, Polij</hi> or <hi>Elgoni, Brigantes Pariſi, Ordouici, alias Ordoluci, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uchlani, Coritani, Trinobantes, Dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, Silures, Dobuni, Atrebatij, Cantij, Regni, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gae, Durotriges, Giruij, Ioeni, Tegenes, Cenimag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, Segonti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ci, Deiri, Venedoti, Bibroci,</hi> with ſome other whome he and others name. And of theſe ſome (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden</hi> plainely ſheweth) poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one,<note place="margin">Camden Britann.</note> others two or three of theſe Shires which now are knowne, &amp; theſe nations of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> are in part named by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> others by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden, Polidore</hi> and others. So that King <hi>Alfreds</hi> diuiſion ſeemeth not altogether new, but rather a reuiuing and more exact deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the old. And this is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:17021:18"/>
of <hi>Polidore,</hi> who in the lawes of <hi>Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> maketh mention by name of Counties, or Shires. Or thoſe Lawes more ſhall be ſaid here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: In the meane time it appeareth that this land was deuided into porcions, or ſhares,<note place="margin">Higden Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lichron Huntingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> euen by the <hi>Britains.</hi> There were alſo amongſt thoſe <hi>Britains,</hi> euen before <hi>Luc us</hi> &amp; <hi>Caeſars</hi> times, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers great Cityes, wherof 28. are named by our Chronicles, and ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iter Britan See the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of England by Hook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> beſides Townes and Caſtles innumerable, as <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſaith and as appeareth by the auncient <hi>Iter Brittanniarum</hi> deſcribed by the <hi>Romans,</hi> which are no ſignes of a barbarous people. For if ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie take his name of a Citie, or Citizen; &amp; Cities, &amp; Citizens ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ruled without goodlawes, the <hi>Britaines</hi> were ciuill, and ruled with good Lawes which were Citizens of many great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And the inconſtancy of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and other <hi>Romanists</hi> is heere to bee noted, which call the <hi>Britaines</hi> barbarous, and yet confeſſe that they had many good Cities, Kinges, Nobles, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, diſcipline of warre, and peace, commerce, and traficke with forraine Nations, and al other parts ef ciuilitie. And the queſtion of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lidore</hi> is ſomewhat ridiculous, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he asketh whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man euer reade of <hi>Canterburie, Bath, Carle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:19"/>
or <hi>Leceſter,</hi> in <hi>Caeſar, Tacitus, Straho</hi> or <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi> No gentle M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Polidore;</hi> but in <hi>Caeſar</hi> wee reade of the City of <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> and of other Cities, and of the Citie of the <hi>Brigantes, Londi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, Louentium</hi> &amp; <hi>Maridunum,</hi> in <hi>Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> &amp; your ſelfe confeſſe in the ſame book that it was a Law among the <hi>Britaines,</hi> that the inner parts of the Iland ſhould not be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtrangers. As for the faſtneſſe of <hi>Caſſibel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> and the painting of their faces; if the ſtorie be wel examined &amp; circumſtances compared, it will eaſily be prooued that ſuch thinges were not originally in the gouernement, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of this our countrie, but were the wilde fruites of long continued ciuill warres, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged amongſt them, proceeding of tirranies in their Princes, ſuperſtition and Idolatry in their Prieſts rebellion, ſedition, murders, thefts, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and diſobedience in the Subiects, ſome of which thinges are to be gathered by the words of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and al of them are laid to their charge by <hi>Gildas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> and other Hiſtories. For ſuch thinges procure the wrath of God to bee powred out vpon them (as ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle,) as <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, France</hi> and other Countries haue, by that meanes receiued ſome barbarous touches, and
<pb facs="tcp:17021:19"/>
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> yet waſted and ſubiect to great calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; deſolation, is an eye witneſſe of the ſame experience, which heeretofore was gouerned with peace ad ciuilitie, and now hath many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples extant of ſtrange immannities. And as theſe are the iuſt plagues inflicted by the diuine Iuſtice vpon our Neighbour Iland for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel, and ſuch offences as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: ſo were the ſame inflicted in thoſe times vpon the <hi>Britaines</hi> for treading vnder foote the light of nature, and the knoweledge of God (which <hi>Gildas</hi> ſignifieth that the firſt inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts had) &amp; many excellent doctrines of Religion, &amp; of juſtice, which were but obſcurelye, &amp; in part preſerued by the <hi>Druidae</hi> and ſome fewe of the better ſort.</p>
               <p>But to returne where wee left, as in other thinges the <hi>Britaines</hi> maintained the manners of the auncients,<note place="margin">Diodor Sic.</note> ſo in that auncient diuiſion of this Land into ſeueral Nations and families, the moſt antique manner of great nations was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. For not onely amongſt the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> but amongſt the <hi>Perſians, Athenians, Romans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Xenophon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uy. et ali.</note> &amp; in this Iland the <hi>Scots</hi> being freer from publike inuaſions, had the like diuiſions, being a poynt of ciuill gouernment, verie neceſſarie for many
<pb facs="tcp:17021:20"/>
good and Politicke conſtitutions, and therefore vſed and preſerued amongſt all the primitiue Nations, as agreeable to reaſon and nature, and is to this day obſerued as moſt conſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 8.</head>
               <p>AS in the diſtribution of perſons, and of the land, the <hi>Britaines</hi> were politick and ciuil: ſo in their proceedings of Lawe, in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in their Sciences, it appeareth that they were not ſo barbarous as hath been taken: for their varieties of excellent learning (to note that by the way) Sir <hi>Iohn Priſe</hi> in his booke to King Edward the ſixt,<note place="margin">Sir Iohn Priſe. Hiſtoriae Brit. Defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio.</note> prooueth that all learned ſciences, were knowne and handled amongſt them. To his booke I ſend thoſe that are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be ſatisfied in that point. And although it may be ſtrongly inferred that a Nation giuen to the ſtuddies of all excellent learnings, muſt needes be poliſhed with good lawes: yet for the more cleere euice heereof, I purpoſe to ſhew that their lawes in particular were moſt iuſt &amp; good, as being deriued out of the lawe of God, written in nature, and in Scripture; and for that reaſon not altered, but tranſmitted to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:20"/>
and that they doe yet remaine amongſt vs, as I ſaid before. Firſt of al vnder fauour I cannot agree, the opinion conceiued by <hi>Gratian</hi> that al thinges by the Lawe of nature, were common,<note place="margin">Part. <hi>1.</hi> Diſt</note> but as I take it the diſtinction of properties was enacted by Almighty God in the beginning, &amp; by him imprinted with other Lawes, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by vertue of the wordes,<note place="margin">Gen. 1. verſ 28.29.</note> Beare rule ouer the earth: which gaue to man, both dominion and propertie of all thinges. And to proue that it was ſo, &amp; that it was ſo vnderſtood,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> who in the verye begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning were ſeueral poſſeſſors of grounds, Lands, Sheep, fruites of the earth, and Cities inhabited, and in the Hiſtoryes of <hi>Abraham, Iob,</hi> and other the Patriarches, there is mencion made of buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, and of diuers offences puniſhed by Lawe. But by what Lawe, if not by the Law of nature? And if the Law of nature be the ſame which is contayned in the Lawe &amp; the Goſpell, as <hi>Gracian</hi> in the firſt entrance of his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons affirmeth; If the terme commaundements be an abridgement or expoſition of the Law of nature, as he ſaith in an other place: And if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of propertyes be inacted, &amp; the deſire of other mens goods forbidden euery where in
<pb facs="tcp:17021:21"/>
the Lawe; the Goſpell, and the tenne comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; then is <hi>Gratian</hi> in this poynt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto him ſelfe. But that it is ſo forbidden, appeareth by the eight and tenth Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and in the firſt to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> where Couetouſnes euen in an heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a ſin,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> which could not be but by the lawe of nature, as it is in that place vrged. For where there is no Lawe, there is no tranſgreſsion ſaith St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; other lawe there is not to condemne a Pagan. Therefore, taking that for a point not hard to be proued, and which all lawes haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as a principall, confeſſed by vertue of that lawe which is euery where the ſame (how-ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome authorities haue ſwayed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) we finde partly by the wordes of <hi>Caeſar</hi> &amp; <hi>Dio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. Eihic</note> that this Iſland had her owne lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diuiſion of groundes, inheritances, Iudges, &amp; the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of properties, that there were certaine courſes of proceedings, and that there were puniſhments for contempts and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.<note place="margin">Dio Lib. 53</note> Firſt <hi>Dio</hi> ſaith that 20. yeares after the comming hither of <hi>Caeſar; Britannia ſuis Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vſa eſt; Britain</hi> vſed her owne Lawes, and what theſe owne Lawes of <hi>Britaine</hi> were, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſheweth: his wordes be theſe: <hi>Druidae fere de
<pb facs="tcp:17021:21"/>
omnibus controuerſiis publicis priuatiſque consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuunt, et ſi quod eſt, admiſſum facinus ſi caedes fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſi de Haereditate, definibus controuerſia eſt, ij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem diſcernunt, praemia praenaſque conſtituunt, ſi quisaut priuatus aut populus, eorum, decreto non stetit, ſacrificijs interdicunt.</hi> The <hi>Druidae</hi> ſaith <hi>Caeſar</hi> (whoſe diſcipline he affirmeth to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out and moſt perfect in <hi>Britaine</hi>) doe iudge for the moſte part of all publike and priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies. If any offence or Homicide be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: or if the controuerſie bee for bounds or inheritance, they doe determine it, appointing punniſhments &amp; rewardes; If any priuate man, or corporation ſtand not to their decree, they forbid them their ſacrifices. &amp;c. vnder the names of offences and Homicides, he comprehendeth all criminall cauſes, vnder controuerſies of lands or inheritance are contained all ciuil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; by the words of controuerſie, iudgement, determination and decree, he ſheweth that they had a certaine forme of proceeding: by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and rewardes, he ſheweth that their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was compulſiue.</p>
               <p>So this teſtimony proueth that they had a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forme of iudgements in thoſe three maine parts, whereof <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> hath compoſed his
<pb facs="tcp:17021:22"/>
whole worke, I ſay <hi>De perſonis rebus et actioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> To touch a few particulars, it muſt needes be inferred vpon <hi>Caeſars</hi> words, that they had a certaine forme of conueyance and courſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce in their lands. For elſe how could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of inheritance and Lands ariſe to be decided in iudgement? Now if any man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well of our auncient forme of conueyance by Feoffment and Liuerie, and the ſolemnitie thereof vſed, not onely after, but before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Ely.</note> he ſhall finde it to bee are like of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly age, wherein the Law of nature was with great wiſdome obſerued.<note place="margin">Gene. 23</note> For if you compare it to the aſſurance of <hi>Abraham,</hi> you ſhall finde like preciſenes of words: I giue thee (ſaith <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phron</hi> which is &amp; euer was, our auncient word, <hi>Do</hi> or <hi>Dedi.</hi> Like deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things: The field of <hi>Ephron</hi> in <hi>Mach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>clah</hi> ouer againſt <hi>Mamre,</hi> the field and the Caue and al the trees &amp;c, like aſsiſtance of witneſſes; in the preſence of my people; and that was alſo our manner, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Norman</hi> conqueſt, and I can finde no beginning vnleſſe I bring it to thoſe auncient times. Our word of inheritance (heires) &amp; that therby th'eldeſt Sonne ſhold inherite, is eyther taken from the ſame lawe of nature, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:17021:22"/>
of the Patriarkes, as <hi>Sem</hi> was heire of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Iaphet</hi> was appointed to dwell in his tents. God ſaith to <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Izhak</hi> ſhalbe thine heire, &amp; <hi>Izhak</hi> made <hi>Iacob</hi> his heire;<note place="margin">Ierim. 49.1</note> Claime is made to ſome part of the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the name of <hi>Iſraels</hi> heires: Or elſe it was inſtituted by K. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> after the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God himſelfe, who made Chriſt the Lord &amp; heire of all things,<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.2</note> and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in parte onely to be heires with him. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly, alſo the manner of our ſucceſsion by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; how one heir is to take after an other, as they are in degrees of proximitie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Report.</hi> 3.</note> is by the moſte exacte reporter of our Lawes S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> (his maieſties Atturnie general) collected and declared, vpon the judgement of God, in the caſe of <hi>Salphahads</hi> daughters,<note place="margin">Numb. 27</note> cyted in <hi>Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffes</hi> caſe; where he alſo obſerueth, that in this point, as almoſt in all others, the common lawe is founded vpon the Law of God. And this our maner of conueyance, and limitation of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I haue not read of in any other nation, neither can finde any other beginning for it. For other conueyances, I finde a patent of King <hi>Arthur</hi> the worthy, and another of one K. <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walchius,</hi> both recited in a Patent of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, made to the Monaſtery of <hi>Glaſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:23"/>
as I learne of Sir <hi>Iohn Priſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſenſio Hiſtor. Brit</note> who ſetteth downe words of King <hi>Henries</hi> Patent, as I wold King <hi>Henrie</hi> had done of the other. Alſo there are many other auncient Charters yet to bee ſeene of manors, landes and liberties, graunted to Abbeyes, Churches &amp; other Religious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes long before the Conqueſt; as of King <hi>Kenre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> to the Abbey of <hi>Euesham,</hi> of others to the Cathedrall Churches of <hi>Landaffe</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dauies</hi> &amp;c. But of all other, moſte excellent is the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent procured by <hi>Turketulus</hi> Lord Chancellor, &amp; Lord of threeſcore Manors, who ſurrendred them all to King <hi>Eared,</hi> and obtained ſixe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, which are alſo named by <hi>Ingulfus,</hi> to bee graunted to the Abbye of <hi>Croyland,</hi> together with many auncient Cuſtomes and new liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; by which may be vnderſtood the vſe of the Common lawe then and long before. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo the Maner of ſuites in Law, &amp; taking diſtreſſes or pledges, &amp; that the defenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhold finde ſureties or mainpernors, a thing verie auncient, wherof we reade in the lawes of King <hi>Ina,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamb. Arc.</note> &amp; yet continuing amongſt vs; I finde ſome ſuch matter noted by <hi>Iob,</hi> where hee ſpeaketh of taking pledges,<note place="margin">Iob. 17.3. et 24.3. et 9.</note> and deſireth that God would put in ſuretie to anſwere him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:23"/>Alſo the particular Lawes of diſtreſſes doe prooue that they are taken out of the word of God. For by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Law no man may diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine a Millſtone;<note place="margin">Deut. 24.</note> a thing ſpecially prouided by God himſelfe. Our auncient kindes of punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as by impriſonments, Fetters, Stocks. &amp;c are named likewiſe in ſeueral places by <hi>Iob.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall executions are deriued from the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>Noah;</hi> whoſoeuer ſheddeth mans blood,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.6</note> by man ſhall his blood bee ſhed. Laſtly our puniſhment by vtlary ſeemeth to be moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, &amp; of the ſame beginning; for take <hi>Bract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> deſcription of vtlary, and compare it with the words of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and both with ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Scripture: and you ſhall finde them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree very neere together. <hi>Bracton</hi> thus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the forfeiture of vtlary. <hi>Forisfacit patriam et regnum, et exul efficitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bracton.</note> 
                  <hi>et talem vocant Augli vt lagh, et alio nomine vocari antiquitus ſolet, Friendleſinan, et ſic videtur Forisfacere amicos; Si quis cum eo communicauerit aliquid, eadem paena pumendus est; Caput gerit Lupinum.</hi> And ſo foorth at large, which Mr. <hi>Stanford</hi> thus briefly comprehendeth.<note place="margin">Stant. L. 3.</note> The out lawe forfeiteth his countrie, his friends, his peace, his law, his right, and his poſſeſsion: which is true euerie way, but
<pb facs="tcp:17021:24"/>
to bee vnderſtood according to the ſeuerall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of vtlaries that are amongſt vs. Now <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> of the <hi>Druidae</hi> ſaith thus:<note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> 
                  <hi>Si quis eorum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto non stetit, ſacrficijs interdicunt. Haec pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na apud eos eſt grauiſsima. Quibus ita est inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum, ij numero impiorum et ſceleratorum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur, ab ijs omnes decedunt, aditum eorum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monemque diffugiunt, ne quid ex contagione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodi accipiant. Neque ijs petentibus ius red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur neque honos vllus communicatur.</hi> Conferre this with the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce pronounced againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> Thou art curſed from the earth,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.</note> when thou til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt the ground, it ſhall not yeeld her ſtrength to thee; a vagabond and a runnagate ſhalt thou be in the earth.</p>
               <p>Thus he forfeited his Countrie and his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the profits of his labour, &amp; of his grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, his friendes and his peace. And this is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our vtlary vſed to this day in capitall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but in leſſer contempts more eaſye and tollerable. Now of theſe thinges before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, haue conſequently followed all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, aſwell in Real as in perſonall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for the proces of diſtreſſe in the parſonall, was but the taking of pledges of the defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, for apparance, and the proceſſe by <hi>Cape</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:24"/>
in the Real, was but the ſeiſing of the Land, for a ſurety to the ſame prepoſe; from whence alſo many other ſecundarie concluſions of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon haue neceſſarilye enſued, as the returne and loſſe of Iſſues, defaults, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, forfeitures, &amp;c. Further in our Chronicles wee reade of Lords &amp; tennants in the daies of <hi>Gorbonian</hi> the good,<note place="margin">Galfrid mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and of fealtie ſworne to the Prince in the time of <hi>Elidurus</hi> the godly,<note place="margin">Pontic. viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> which of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were accompained with tenures, ſeruices, diſtreſſes, and ſuch like: And thus much be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the auncient viſible footeſteppes, of the lawe of nature, which were before <hi>Lucius;</hi> Of which you may reade alſo in the learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the aboue named, Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> before the third Booke of his Reportes, where he citeth the ſentence of <hi>Caeſar:</hi> ſaying that the diſcipline of the <hi>Druidae</hi> was found out in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannia,</hi> and that we had ſome formes of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the <hi>Greek;</hi> which may well bee; but you ſee the grounds and beginnings are much more apparant to bee ſeene in the records of that firſt age deſcribed in the ſacred Hiſtory, &amp; doe yet remaine amongſt vs.</p>
               <p>Now followeth to ſpeake of the ordinances inſtituted by our auncient <hi>Britain</hi> Kings, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:17021:25"/>
to the word of God; and to this day alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning: and firſt of the Lawes of <hi>Mulmutius</hi> &amp; others which were called the Marchen law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 9.</head>
               <p>ALthough concerning the Hiſtorie of <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> there may bee ſome reaſons to doubt which learned men haue gathered, yet, why there ſhould not be one <hi>Brit</hi> or <hi>Brute</hi> King of this Land, whoſe Pedegree Sir <hi>Iohn Priſe</hi> out of an auncient Chronicle deriueth from <hi>Iaphet:</hi> And if there were no ſuch <hi>Brit,</hi> yet why the whole Hiſtorie of Britaine Princes ſhould for the fabulous interpoſition of one or two men be reiected, as ſome haue done? I ſee no reaſon ſeeing the concurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonies of diuers Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of great credit, which S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>I. Priſe</hi> citeth, &amp; the concordance of the Scottiſh Hiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory in many thinges, and that of ſome of thoſe Princes remains to this day, appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of others credible Hiſtories, of others the moſte ineuitable teſtimony of auncient Lawes. The learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cambden</hi> a iudicious examiner of theſe things,<note place="margin">Cambden in Britanniae</note> offereth to prooue that the famous <hi>Brennus</hi> that ouerranne <hi>Italy,</hi> was King of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> (a thing which the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Io. Priſe</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie
<pb facs="tcp:17021:25"/>
moſt learnedly performed:) to me it is as well prooued that <hi>Mulmutius</hi> his Father was King likewiſe of this Land: neither doe I thinke the warres of the one ſo glorious, as the Lawes of the other. But if any be ſo wilfully ignorant, as to deny, not onely the Hiſtorie of Brit, but of his ſucceſſors: Let them name if they can imagine, who built theſe auncient Monnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Ludgate, Bellingſgate, Caerebranke or the Citye of Yorke, <hi>Carleil,</hi> and <hi>Caercoil</hi> or Colcheſter and ſuch like? and who made theſe auncient Lawes, called the <hi>Mulmutian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ponticus vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>run Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Higden. Ceſt lib. <hi>1.</hi> Galfrid mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Baleus. Hooker. Pol. virgil.</note> &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Lawes, of which we haue to ſpeake. Many writers which without queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſee, or might ſee and reade the writinges of <hi>Gildas</hi> the wiſe Prieſt, and <hi>Alfred</hi> the excellent Prince, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly avouch that <hi>Mulmutius Dunwallo</hi> Father of <hi>Belinus</hi> and <hi>Brennus,</hi> eſtabliſhed thoſe Lawes which were afterward called <hi>Mulmutinae,</hi> which <hi>Gildas</hi> tranſlated into Latin, as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelfe (ſay they) and afterwards King <hi>Alfred</hi> turned them into Engliſh. Out of which wordes I gather theſe obſeruations, firſt that there was ſuch a King and hee made theſe Lawes without queſtion. Secondly that theſe Lawes were verie iuſt, for elſe ſuch men as <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:26"/>
and <hi>Alfred</hi> would not haue tranſlated and preſerued them. Thirdly that they doe yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine amongſt our common Lawes, although hardly to be diſcerned which they bee: for the ſame writers teſtifie that they being mingled amongſt the lawes of <hi>Alfred,</hi> were by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> reduced to one common Law, which the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man yeelded vnto, and himſelfe and all his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors are ſworne to obſerue them.<note place="margin">Pontic. viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Monemuth.</note> And ſo ſay <hi>viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nius &amp; Monemuthenſis. Leges Patris quae Molmutinae dicebantur instituit inter Britones quae vſque ad hoc tempus celebrantur inter An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glos.</hi> So alſo ſaith <hi>Higden:</hi> where ſpeaking firſt of the Marchen Lawe, containing both Lawes of <hi>Mulmutius</hi> and <hi>Mertia,</hi> and of the <hi>Dane</hi> Law, &amp; weſt <hi>Saxon</hi> Law, <hi>Ex his tribus Legibus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Sanctus Edwardus tertius vnam Legem commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem edidit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtrencis. Pol. virgil.</note> 
                  <hi>que Leges Edwardi vſque hodie vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur:</hi> of theſe three lawes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> the third made one common Law, which to this day are called the Lawes of <hi>Edward.</hi> Beholde therefore the Fathers, yea and the very name of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law. Beholde a full proofe of Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcues</hi> teſtimonye concerning our Lawes. Some particulars wherof as they were in thoſe times, are alſo mencioned in Chronicles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:26"/>For by <hi>Polidore</hi> it is thus recorded:<note place="margin">Pol Virgil.</note> 
                  <hi>Mulmutius ius atque Leges nouas, et illas quidem ſalutares dedit, quas deinceps Mulmitianas Leges appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Templa deorum immortalum Loco aſyli omnibus ad ea confugientibus eſſe constituit;</hi> &amp; a little after, <hi>Pondera ac menſuras rebus vendendis emendiſque poſuit, fures et noxium omne genus hominum ſeueriſſime puniuit, fecit quamplures vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, decreuit que in quam Latitudinem fieri debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ac Lege ſanxit earum ius ad Principem dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat pertinere: eiuſque iuris violatoribus, atque ijs qui in illis maleficium aliquod facerent consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit paenas: praeterea vt ne terra vacaret, neue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus rei frumentariae inopia frequenter premere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut minueretur, ſi pecora ſola occuparent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gros, qui ab hominibus coli deberent, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituit quot quiſque Comitatus aratra haberet,</hi> and ſo foorth: where you ſee that he made lawes for Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for weights, for meaſures: againſt theft, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and other offences: for high waies &amp; Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances, and for tillage and Husbandrie: and by the words you may eaſily gather, that they were the ſame, or much to the ſame effect, as they are now, either continuing in the common Law, or reuiued by Statutes: and that in thoſe daies alſo the land was deuided into certaine parts, which
<pb facs="tcp:17021:27"/>
are now called Counties. <hi>Brecus</hi> and <hi>Ferguſius</hi> likewiſe in Scotland, neere about the ſame time alſo made Lawes for diuiſion of their Land in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Tribes, hundreds, and wapentakes ſaith the Chronicle, and for puniſhment of murder, theft and other offences.</p>
               <p>Againe by <hi>Higden</hi> it is thus recorded <hi>Anno mundi</hi> 3529. <hi>ante Christum</hi> 445. <hi>Mulmutius</hi> King of the <hi>Britaines</hi> the 23, but the firſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, ordained that Churches Plowes, Cities and High-waies, ſhould inioy a Priuiledge or libertie. This <hi>Higden</hi> expoundeth to be a kinde of Sanctuarie, that if any offender did fly to any of theſe, he ſhould no further be purſewed but ſuffered to eſcape, which interpretation cannot be made but onely of the Church, and therfore to be let paſſe, as made by a Monke ignorant of Law.</p>
               <p>But our common Lawe giueth a ſound and verie conſonant expoſition. For euen from the moſt auncient times to this day, there is a kinde of priuiledge in vſe, that theſe foure ſhould bee free from diſtreſſe. For no man ought to be diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayned by the beaſtes of his Plowe, nor in high waies, nor in Markets or Churches. This free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from diſtreſſe then I take to be the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:17021:27"/>
ordayned by <hi>Mulmutius,</hi> chiefly becauſe it is indifferently commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to al the foure things aboue mencioned:<note place="margin">Marlebr. Cap. <hi>2.</hi> et <hi>15</hi> w. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>16 51.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> Art. Cleri. Cap. <hi>9.</hi> Fitz. N.B. <hi>90.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; although diuers later ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes doe confirme &amp; enlarge this priuiledge to ſome one or other of the foure, yet none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> name altogether, as they were in <hi>Mulmutius</hi> Law, and by the likenes of the Priuiledge it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth they were ioyned at firſt, Alſo by the words of <hi>Articuli Cleri:</hi> it ſeemeth to bee more au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient then the ſtatutes. For the Clergie there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained of diſtreſſes taken in their glebe as a wrong. Beſides ſome of the writs made vpon this priuiledge haue theſe words <hi>Contra Legem et conſuetudinem Regn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> which for the moſt part is intended to be the moſte auncient common Law: yet if this interpretation be not accepted: then take another collected vpon the auncient Lawes of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and the <hi>Norman.</hi> They ſaie that the Church hath a priuiledge which they call <hi>Pacem,</hi> and is vnderſtood the Sanctuarie. The foure waies haue a peace, which is, that all Nuſances in them ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended (note the antiquitie of our Lawes, of Nuſanz.) But for markets and plowes, no other priuiledge can be heard of, but onely this wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue ſpoken, to be free from diſtreſſe, which
<pb facs="tcp:17021:28"/>
is ſtill continued. And this <hi>Polidor</hi> ſeemeth to ſay, expounding the law of <hi>Mulmutius,</hi> to bee, that the beaſtes of the plow ought not to be led away for debt, ſo long as the debtor had other goods. Now if the Priuiledge from diſtreſſe was ſo auncient, it muſt needes follow that diſtreſſes were much more aunciently in vſe as I noted alſo before. And from the vſe of diſtreſſes by ſecundary concluſions and deductions of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, followed many Lawes amongſt vs, yet in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon practiſe; as of Attornments, Repleuies, Auouries, Tenures Seruices: <hi>Quid Iuris clamat, quem redditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reddit. Per quae ſeruicia</hi> &amp; ſuch like, which by neceſſitie muſt be vnderſtood, where diſtreſſes are frequent, and ſo much of the <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutian</hi> Lawe. Now followeth of King <hi>Lucius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 10.</head>
               <p>BY many ſteppes and degrees I am come to the Lucid ſtarre of Britaine, well deſeruing that name, for that in his time, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iuſtice, &amp; gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhine more brightly in this kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in the hiſtory of him, &amp; his ſuccſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors the Readers may obſerue three things: Firſt that this Nation aboue all Nations of the earth
<pb facs="tcp:17021:28"/>
(except the Hebrewes) hath had moſt vertuous, religious &amp; Godly Princes. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that as our auncient lawes were moſte righteous, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from the lawes of God written in nature: So <hi>Lucius</hi> and his ſucceſſors eſtabliſhed one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch good and iuſt Lawes, as were agreeable to Chriſtianitie, and deriued out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Thirdly that all calamities of this Land hath proceeded of publike &amp; notorious crimes againſt God and his ſeruants, our good Princes, and againſt religion and religious lawes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Lucius</hi> himſelfe, I cited before the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of King <hi>Alfred,</hi> a witneſſe farre aboue all exception: who ſaith directly and expreſly in his Lawes, that vpon the propagation of the Goſpel, when many men receiued the faith of Chriſt as well in England as in other regions, certaine Synods, aſwel of Biſhoppes, as of other moſt noble wiſe men were gathered, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed puniſhments for offendors. And a little after, theſe Sanctions or Lawes, I <hi>Alfred</hi> King haue collected &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to writing, where he ſpeaketh of certaine Sinodes, of Biſhops &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; wiſe men; it muſt needes be mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laments, as we ſhewed before. For wee reade of no generall counſell in Britaine, and of Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb facs="tcp:17021:29"/>
Sinodes, it cannot be intended; where hee ſaith that they were gathered vpon the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpell, he ſignifieth the time of King <hi>Lucius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beda. L. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> when the Goſpell was firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely receaued in this Land, For it cannot bee vnderſtood of the Chriſtian <hi>Saxons,</hi> for of them he ſpeaketh by name afterwards, ſaying that he vſed choice and iudgement in refuſing ſome of their lawes, and taking others; whereof I inferre firſt that thoſe words before were meant of the firſt Chriſtian <hi>Britaines,</hi> (whom he nameth not becauſe they were enemies to the <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>) Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that thoſe Britiſh lawes were more ſincere &amp; agreeable to Godlynes then the <hi>Saxon.</hi> Thirdly that thoſe ſanctions by him collected, are ſome of the auncient common Lawes, which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, for that we finde no other collection of Lawes made by him: But this all Hiſtories teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he tranſlated into <hi>Saxon</hi> the ſame which <hi>Gildas</hi> turned into Latin, &amp; that the ſame were gathered into our common Law by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> and called Saint <hi>Edwards</hi> lawes.</p>
               <p>Beſides it cannot be ſayd that theſe good lawes were made by any other, but onely by <hi>Lucius,</hi> for neither was any other of the Britaine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo Godly &amp; religious, as he, neither had any
<pb facs="tcp:17021:29"/>
of his ſucceſſors ſuch peaceable poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Land or conueniency to make lawes as he had. For immediately after his death, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally till the Saxons time, the whole ſtate trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with forein and inteſtine enemies. Laſtly the teſtimony of <hi>Polidore</hi> confirmeth this,<note place="margin">Pol. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</note> who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this moſte honorable teſtimonie of King <hi>Lucius:</hi> that he left his kingdome aſwell <hi>Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis inſtitutis prouectum</hi> aduaunced or amended with the beſt inſtitutions or Lawes, as <hi>diuina re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione auctum;</hi> ſo that without queſtion it is that he made ſome of our Lawes.</p>
               <p>But particularly which of theſe lawes or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions now extant were enacted by <hi>Lucius,</hi> it is hard to ſay: yet to ſpeake my opinion, I think firſt our Lawes of fines and amercements was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in his time. For ſo ſaith <hi>Alfred,</hi> that thoſe firſt Chriſtian Parlaments conſiſting of Biſhops &amp; moſt noble wiſe men, being taught by the mercifulneſſe of Chriſt, did appoint for euerie firſt offender a pecuniary paine, where you ſee not onely the thing, but almoſt the verie name of <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> which is vſed to this day in amercenents, and is afterwards frequently vſed in the Saxon and Norman Lawes, and this was for ſmaller offences. But
<pb facs="tcp:17021:30"/>
for the greateſt, the words of <hi>Alfred</hi> goe further; ſaying of the ſame firſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <hi>Proditori tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tummodo ac Dommim defertori hanc initiorem paenam haud infligendam exiſtimarunt, quippe qui eiuſmodi viro minime parcendum cenſuerunt tum quod Deus contemptores ſui omni miſeratione indignos voluit, tum quod Christus illorum qui ei mortem obtulerunt non est omnino miſertus.</hi> Where you ſee that by the teſtimonie of <hi>Alfred</hi> they tooke the preſident of their Law againſt Treaſon,<note place="margin">Lamb. Arc.</note> from the examples of Chriſt and of God. What was that Lawe? It followeth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.<note place="margin">In leg. Alf. Cap. <hi>4</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui capiti et ſaluti Regis perfidioſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diabitur vita et fortunis eius omnibus priuator.</hi> that the Traytor ſhould forfeit, life, Lands, and goods.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Actes.</hi> 1.</note> So was <hi>Iudas</hi> puniſhed and that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Elfredus</hi> felt being conuicted of treaſon in the daies of King <hi>Athelſtane</hi> as appeareth by the ſaid Kings Charter,<note place="margin">Fox in men.</note> recited by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fox:</hi> here alſo appeareth not onely the Eſchet which you ſee is expreſſely ſet downe in the words, but alſo trialls, for it would be iniurious &amp; vaine to ſet downe a puniſhment for offences, and not ſet downe a courſe how the offender might be cleered or condemned: and it is moſte vnlikely, that King <hi>Lucius</hi> and thoſe firſt Chriſtians wold
<pb facs="tcp:17021:30"/>
imitate God and Chriſt in ſeueritie of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not much more ſtudie to imitate him in the Iuſtice &amp; ſinceritie of their Trialles.</p>
               <p>Therfore I think that the ſame <hi>Lucius</hi> ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Tryals by twelue, &amp; that according to the example of Chriſt. For, that it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Sir Iohn Forteſcue.</note> the learned Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> hath fully prooued, and whoſoeuer ſhall conſider of it indifferently, ſhall finde that it is the moſte righteous and Godly courſe that euer was found out, and therefore moſte likely to proceede from the piety of that holy King.</p>
               <p>Alſo in that pureſt age of Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">Gra. Diſt. <hi>11.</hi> et Diſt. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> it was held for a ground, that firſt the Scriptures ought to be ſearched, whether any rule might bee found for the action intended, or not; if not, then <hi>Mos populi dei et Sanctorum exempla</hi> the manner of Gods people and the examples of holy men were to be followed.</p>
               <p>And if holy men ought to be imitated, then who if not our moſte holy Sauiour? as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5 1. Cor. 11.</note> Be followers of God as deere Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and be followers of mee as I am of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quo est detestabilior iſtorum immanitas:</hi> So much the more is their crueltie to be abhorred, which labour to hide, not onely the words, but
<pb facs="tcp:17021:31"/>
alſo the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of Chriſt away from vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay <hi>Lucius</hi> did inſtitute the trial of al mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in fact,<note place="margin">Act. 1, 22. et 10 41. Iohn. 15.27</note> to be by twelue witneſſes, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ordayned, &amp; choſe twelue to beare witneſſe of his reſurrection; neither doe I finde any other law preſident or exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple from whence this manner of Trialls ſhould be taken. But I finde that the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Elutherius,</hi> from whom <hi>Lucius</hi> had much of his light, vſed the ſame rule &amp; practiſe, for that good Biſhop <hi>Iuxta or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationem Apoſtolorum</hi> according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ordinance,<note place="margin">Faſcic. Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p.</note> did decree that no meates v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall for mankinde ſhould be refuſed of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians; And <hi>Exemplo Chriſti</hi> by the example of Chriſt, ordained that none ſhould be regraded before he were condemned.</p>
               <p>Thus they tooke a rule or preſident for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing out of the Scripture. And the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the contrarie is not to be obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for although he ſaieth that at the mouth of two or three, an offender ſhall die; yet he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the negatiue, that more ſhould not be vſed. Therefore the Apoſtolicall Canons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited, and the example of our Sauiour in the affirmatiue was a better warrant. And it is moſt apparant that iuries were vſed among
<pb facs="tcp:17021:31"/>
the Chsiſtian <hi>Britaines</hi> and before the <hi>Saxon</hi> times; for proofe whereof, although in mine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, the teſtimony of the profoundly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> ſhould bee ſufficient ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expreſſely that theſe lawes were vſed in the time of the <hi>Britaines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir. Iohn Forteſcue.</note> yet for the further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of thoſe that leane to much to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Polidor</hi> and other Italians, I will adde more reaſons &amp; authorities to the ſame point. Firſt the moſt learned Antiquary of our Nation M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Camden Britannae.</note> ſheweth plainely that it was not inuented by the Conqueror, (as <hi>Polidor</hi> ſaith,) but it was in vſe in the daies of King <hi>Etheldred</hi> the <hi>Saxon;</hi> Secondly the moſt excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of our Lawes,<note place="margin">Praef in L. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> before cited, prooueth by ſubſtantiall records, that this triall was before the Conqueſt. So there are three witneſſes euerie one of exceeding great learning againſt one Maiſter <hi>Polidor.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Tantae molis erat Romanam excindere gentem.</q>
               <p>Such a labour it is to ouerthrowe theſe Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an opinions, of which our nation is too fondly credulous. But let vs goe forward, &amp; although my ſimple diſcourſe can adde no weight vnto their moſt graue iudgements, eſpecially the laſt cited, which is grounded vpon records: yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:17021:32"/>
fauour, I will adioyne ſome other teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and proofes. In the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, when by all mens conſent our Iudges were moſt exactly learned (as in deede it was a time excelling, not onely in Martiall glorie, but in learning and wiſdome) I finde M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Belknap</hi> a reuerend Iudge, concurring in opinon, with theſe before named.<note place="margin">41. <hi>E.</hi> 3.31.</note> The Law (ſaith hee) was founded in this, that euery Inqueſt ſhold be taken <hi>Per duodecim liberos et legales homines et non per pauciores.</hi> If it were a foundation of the common law, then without queſtion it was one of the firſt Lawes; and we muſt needes confeſſe that no Law can be without tryalls, and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proued that euer any other triall was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, beſides this in pleas of land or inherirance in this kingdome.</p>
               <p>But to make it yet more plaine, the City of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is and was in the times of the <hi>Britaines,</hi> by the confeſſion of many learned writers, namely <hi>Caeſar Tacitus, Ptolomy, Ammianus Marcellinus, Gildas Galfridus &amp;c.</hi> a moſte auncient City, a place of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ruled by a gouernor, the ſea of a Flamine or Biſhop, not a faſtenes of the woodes as ſome haue imagined vpon the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and vncertaine words of authors, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:17021:32"/>
ſaw it, but frequented and cclebrated with concourſe of Merchants &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of commerce as <hi>Tacitus</hi> affirmeth. Now I pray you beholde with the eyes of your minde, the forme of ſuch a Citie: and tell mee how you can imagine it to ſtand without a Court of Iuſtice, the bond of commerce, for the deciding of controuerſies? or how you can imagine that ſuch a Court ſhould be without a due forme of Trialls? But leaſt I may ſeeme to deale by immagination; for the firſt point that it had a Court;<note place="margin">Calf. Mon. Pontic. vir.</note> 
                  <hi>Galfridus Mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muthenſis</hi> and <hi>Ponticus virunnius</hi> out of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Britiſh Hiſtorie, doe teſtifie in playne words; that in the daies of <hi>Iulius Caeſar, Irelgas,</hi> Nephew of <hi>Caſsibellan,</hi> being ſlaine by <hi>Cuelinus,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Androgeus</hi> Gouernor or Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of London, a commaundement was giuen to <hi>Androgeus</hi> to bring <hi>Cuelinus</hi> to the K. Court, there to receiue Iuſtice: his anſwere was <hi>Seſe ſuam habere curiam, et in illa definiri debere quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid alquis in homines ſuos clamaret, ſi ergo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitudinem de Cuelino decreuiſſet appetere ipſam in vrbe Trinobantum ex veterum traditione fieri praeciperet.</hi> He alledgeth that hee hath his Court, wherin ought to be determined whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer any man laide to the charge of his men, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17021:33"/>
that right ought to be done vnto them in the Citie of London according to the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome. For the ſecond point, if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Polidor</hi> will not giue vs leaue to thinke that London had this iuriſdiction in <hi>Caeſars</hi> time; yet without his leaue, I wil proue by many infallible records that the ſame City of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had this iuriſdict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, and namely this tryal by twelue in the time of the <hi>Britaines,</hi> thus:</p>
               <p>This City of London hath and had alwaies from time out of minde their Huſtings, &amp; the writ of right in London tryable by twelue; the Aſsiſe of Freſhforce tryable by twelue; and the tryall of pleas of the Crowne by twelue; it muſt needes be that theſe Liberties were begun eyther by Parlament or preſcription, eyther in the time of the Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of the Saxons, or of the Britaines. But in 14. <hi>E.</hi> 2. when they muſt needes haue knowne if there had bin any Patent or Acte of Parlament, either of the <hi>Saxons</hi> or <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> for it. <hi>A quo warranto in Itinere in Turri London</hi> being brought, for theſe and other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: The cominaltie of that City make their claime to the reſt by ſeueral Pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, but to theſe by auncient cuſtome and preſcription confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Charters in theſe words. <hi>Quoad articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
<pb facs="tcp:17021:33"/>
quod &amp;c proferunt cartam Henrici aui Regis nunc in qua continetur quod idem H. rex,</hi> 16. <hi>die Marcij Anno regni ſui vndecimo conceſsit ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus predictis, quod Huſtingum ſemel tantum in hebdomada tenatur ſecundum conſuetudmem ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatis. Et proferunt aliam carta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eiusdem Domini H. Regis in qua continetur quod idem Dominus Henricus Rex</hi> 20. <hi>die Martij Anno regni ſui</hi> 52. <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſſit ciuibus ſuis London quod de placitis ad co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronam pertinentibus de his maxime quae infra ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatem praedictam et eius ſuburbia fieri conting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, ſe poſſunt diſrationare ſecundum antiquam conſuetudinem ciuitatis praedictae.</hi> By theſe Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters you ſee, that the pleas aforeſaid are to be proceeded and tried according to the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or cuſtome of the Citie, &amp; ſo are the words of the Aſsiſe of Freſhforce. By the way the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is to vnderſtand, that preſcription or cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome here, is not ſaid to be the continuance of many yeres, as 50.60. or an hundred: But that in Law is ſaid to be by preſcription, the beginning whereof cannot be proued by any record, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or lawul teſtimony, &amp; ſuch a preſcription is heere to be vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>Now that the cuſtome &amp; ſuch a preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of London is &amp; was in the Conquerors time and
<pb facs="tcp:17021:34"/>
before, that their trialls ſhould be by a Iurie of twelue,<note place="margin">Fit. N.B. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> all their records teſtifie: The reuerend Iudge <hi>Fitsherbert</hi> teſtifieth and moſt euidently the Record of the <hi>Quo warranto</hi> aboue cited teſtifieth, for ſo it goeth forward, <hi>Quoad articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum predictum quod ipſi de placitis ad coronam Regis pertinentibus ſe poſsint diſrationare ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum antiquam conſuetudinem ciuitatis; dictum est eis periusticiarios quod declarent Curiae modum et formam huiuſmodi diſrationamenti et conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis. Qui dicunt quod Antiqua conſuetudo ciuitatis eſt quod ſiquis liber ciuitatis aliquod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictum fecerit per quod periculum vitae incurrere debeat, et vſque Iter Iusticiariorum manucaptus fuerit, et inde in Itinere poſtea, ſit ad Ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitus, ſe diſrationare poteſt per duodecim Iurato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res patrie ſecundum Legem communem vel per magnam Legem Ciuitatis, viz. per triginta ſex legales homines ciuitatis. &amp;c.</hi> Nothing can bee more plainely proued, then the point in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is by this record: viz. that the trial by twelue was vſed both by the common Law, and by the moſt auncient cuſtome of London, I ſay by cuſtome, whereof no beginning could be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Wel then it was cleere in the times of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>Edward.</hi> 1. and <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:17021:34"/>
is alſo proued not onely by this record, but by their great Charter, for they giue them no new liberties, but <hi>Ciuitas London habeat omnes anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas conſuetudines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mag. Car.</note> &amp; this was within two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after the Conqueror: if any Law or Patent had bene made of it in al that time; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, they would haue pleaded the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or Law, and not preſcription. For a Satute or patent doth determine a preſcription.</p>
               <p>The Conqueror, dooth he make them any graunt or Patent heereof, or dooth <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor one of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Princes, graunt any ſuch matter or make mention that any ſuch thing was graunted by patent vnto London? <hi>Ne my:</hi> Not a minim of any ſuch matter, It is written in their Lawes,<note place="margin">Lamb. Arc. in Leg. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi. Liber Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordorum. London Dunthorne</note> 
                  <hi>Debet etiam in London quae caput eſt regni et Legum, ſemper curia Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis ſingulis Septimanis die Lunae Huſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſe dere et teneri,</hi> Marke how it agreeth with the patent before pleaded. <hi>In ea itaque ſuper ſunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua compota et ambigua placita coronae et curiae domini regis totius Regni predicti quae haec vſque et co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudines ſuas vna se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per in violabilitate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruat vbicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que ipſe rex fuerit ſiue in expedicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſiue alibit, propter fatigationem gentium et po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulorum regni iuxta veteres Conſuetudines bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb facs="tcp:17021:35"/>
patrum et predeceſſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principum et proceru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et ſapientu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſentorum totius regni predicti.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the Charter of K. William the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Chron.</note> Beholde then here is no new inſtitution menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned neither by the Conqueror nor by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, but ſtill the auncient cuſtomes.</p>
               <p>And if this had bene by patent or Parlament of any <hi>Saxon</hi> Prince; without all queſtion theſe two Princes would haue knowne it. For all the <hi>Saxon</hi> gouernment in peace from the firſt King vnto the laſt was not aboue 300. yeeres, &amp; both <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>VVilliam</hi> were moſt diligent ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Regiſters of all the lawes, Liberties &amp; Cuſtomes of their kingdome, as appeareth by the Domeſday Booke, and by that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Houeden</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>Beſides in the <hi>Saxon</hi> times, not a peece of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d paſſed from the Crowne, and much leſſe any liberties or Iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are parcel of the royal prerogatiue without Patent, as appeareth by the manifolde patents of manors, Landes, &amp; Liberties made to Churches and Monaſteries, whereof thoſe that belonged to the Abby of Croyland,<note place="margin">Ingulfus Hiſtoria E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lienſis.</note> are faithfully recorded by <hi>Ingulfus,</hi> thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Ely</hi> by another; and others are to be ſeene in the Churches that remaine.</p>
               <p>The City of London therefore had this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie
<pb facs="tcp:17021:35"/>
and Maner of trial in the <hi>Normans</hi> time, not by patent or new Law, but by preſcription; they had it in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time not by patent or new Law: therefore by preſcription, &amp; it muſt needes bee true, that they had it from a time whereof no proofe could be made, that is, long before the <hi>Saxons.</hi> I ſay by preſcription as it is pleaded euen from the Britaines. And this that I haue ſaid of London, I may ſay of all aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cities where they haue like cuſtomes and Liberties; yea the auncient hundred, Courts, Shiermotes, Wardmotes, Swainmotes, Leets, and Wapentakes, which are often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned in the <hi>Saxons</hi> Lawes as thinges in vſe. Let any man ſhew me, what other kinde of triall or inquiſition, they had then this, and <hi>Quo warranto</hi> by what law they had this, but by like preſcription. If you bring foorth the triall by fire and water called <hi>Ordell,</hi> it was by al like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood but a ſuperſtitious inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> times,<note place="margin">In Legibus Canuti de Foreſta.</note> &amp; was vſed onely in criminall cauſes where the truth could not otherwiſe be known as appeareth by the Law of <hi>Canutus.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Conqueror in his abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund did ſomething of his owne head,<note place="margin">Houeden Lamb.</note> yet it appereth plainely that when by the earneſt
<pb facs="tcp:17021:36"/>
intreaty of his Nobles, he was perſwaded to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the former lawes; he then by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his Nobles, and according to the courſe and common Lawes of the Realme, impanelled twelue men of euerie Shire, to inquire &amp; make a true preſentment of the ſaid auncient Lawes and cuſtomes, for ſo be the words: <hi>Electi de ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis totius patriae comitatibus duodecim viri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamb. Arc. Houeden.</note> 
                  <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiurando Coram Rege primum confirmauerunt, vt quoad poſsent recto tramite incedentes, nec ad dextra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec ad ſinistra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuertentes, legum ſuarum, et conſuetudinum, ſancita patefacerent &amp;c.</hi> And amongſt the reſt, they make mencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of London, which I cited before. I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here, that the footeſteps of this triall, are found in the lawes of <hi>Etheldred</hi> made at wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which is cited by Maiſter <hi>Camden;</hi> nor of the ordinance, made for the mountainers of Wales:<note place="margin">Malmes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury. Huntingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ethelwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Hiſtoria E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remaining with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Cotton. Ingulfus.</note> nor of the law of <hi>Kennethus,</hi> the famous Scottiſh King about the yere of our Sauiour Chriſt, 840. mentioning ſome ſuch matter; nor of the learned &amp; diligent Hiſtorians, that liued neere about the conqueſt: &amp; might eaſily haue tolde vs if any ſuch thing had been begun by the Saxons; nor of the Hiſtorie of <hi>Ely,</hi> written before the conqueſt: and <hi>Ingulfus</hi> ſoone after,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:36"/>
plainly ſpeaking of Mannors, Feoffements, Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty Courts, Tearmes at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in an aſſiſe or writ of right, as of thinges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> common and vſuall.</p>
               <p>We read alſo of Parlaments, wapentakes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, fealties, diſcents from the Grandfather to the Nephew, <hi>Eſchets</hi> to the King for want of heires, in the daies of <hi>Aurelius Ambroſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leland. Hooker. Galf. Mon. Gildas.</note> and of <hi>Arthur</hi> the worthy, &amp; ſtreight way after, <hi>Gildas</hi> maketh mencion of Courts, Iudges, Freſhſuit after thieues, &amp; Iudgements which could not be without trialls. By all which I thinke it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that theſe points of common law, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe trialls by twelue, are of moſt auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, according to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law, and vſed amongſt other cuſtomes of the citie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don before the times of the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Norman</hi> Princes, of whome no ſuch Libertie or courſe of proceeding could be gotten without patent, and no other forme of auncient tryalls doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: vpon which I conclude, as before, that they had it in the times of the <hi>Britaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame is prooued by al the auncient and new records of Aſsiſes, of Freſhforce, of writs of right, and other tryalles in London, which muſt bee all falſified and many thouſands
<pb facs="tcp:17021:37"/>
of records beſides, if wee ouerthrowe this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. And this being ſo conſonant to the iudgments of thoſe excellent men before cited, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den, Belknap,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Io. Forteſcue,</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ed. Cook,</hi> Let vs now leaue Maiſter <hi>Polidor</hi> &amp; his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which either neuer ſaw or did not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, our auncient Hiſtories and Records; let vs leaue them (I ſay) to their owne imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with this admonition to all diſcreet Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries, that they be not ouer-haſty to beleeue either the <hi>Roman</hi> or other Authors, ſpeaking of the <hi>Britaines</hi> thire enemies, but holding them ſuſpect for partialitie or ignorance, which may eaſily appeare to euerie iudiciall Reader, let vs followe the true groundes confirmed by theſe faithfull Monuments of our Lawes, and the Hiſtories thereunto agreeing. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſcertained, it is eaſie now to beholde, from whence all our Aſsiſes of nouel diſeiſin of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danceſter, of darrain preſentment, our great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſes, Iuries, Challenges &amp; the reſt, of which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bracton</hi> at large diſcourſeth, are lineally deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, being as I take it the greateſt part of our common Lawes, and it appereth by that which is before ſpoken, that theſe alſo are moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scripture of God; whereupon I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="tcp:17021:37"/>
fully, that all our common Lawes was in vſe in the <hi>Britaines</hi> time long before the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> howſoeuer ſuppreſſed &amp; the bookes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of defaced by forreine inuaſions, and inteſtine diſſentions. And thus much of <hi>Lucius</hi> and the <hi>Britaines.</hi> Now of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 11.</head>
               <p>IT hath bene a worke of the ſpecial prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Almightie God, &amp; of his infinite mercie to this Iland, in the middes of Poetical fables wherwith the Britiſh Hiſtories haue bene mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and of thoſe Barbarous inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which haue waſted and ſpoyled them, to leaue vs yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine remnants and monuments, whereby to iudge of thoſe long paſt Antiquities; in iudging wherof, men by taking contrarie courſes, haue made the controuerſie more difficult, that the truth fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out might be the better confirmed. For ſome haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to fauour the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Hiſtorie ſo much, as to abrogate all faith and credit from the Britiſh, as if the ambitious Romanes &amp; <hi>Caeſar</hi> would ſay nothing for their owne aduantage, who of all others moſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of glorie is iuſtly noted by <hi>Suetonius, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17021:38"/>
and <hi>Aſinius Pollio</hi> to haue written his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries, as much as he might, to ſaue his owne Honour, eſpeciallye of his Actions in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote places.</p>
               <p>Others haue gone ſo farre to the bowehand, as to fauour all the vanities of the Poeticall Bardes, as if nothing could bee denied, which they had once turned into Rythme. But that God which came into the world to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the truth (ſo much doth he loue it) hath left vs rules and directions to trie out the verity of auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t times. By the mouth of two or three witneſſes, euerie word ſhall be confirmed ſayth <hi>Moſes,</hi> and (as it is moſte certaine) truth cannot be ſo much oppreſſed as to be vtterly deſtitute of proofes. Let therefore the proofe reſt vpon witneſſes and compariſon of circumſtances, &amp; it will appreare as Sir <hi>Iohn Priſe</hi> truely auerreth and learnedly prooueth, that the Britiſh Story is in many things more to be credited then <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> and <hi>Polidore,</hi> and other <hi>Italians.</hi> Beſides the Scottiſh Hiſtorie agreeing in many things with vs, manifeſtly conuinceth the <hi>Romanes</hi> of their Arrogancie and vanitie, and with all miniſtreth further groundes, not onely to proue the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and ſincerity of our common Lawes, but
<pb facs="tcp:17021:38"/>
that the ſame or others much like obtained in Scotland alſo, as well as heere, which may bee ſeene by the Lawes of <hi>Brechus</hi> &amp; <hi>Ferguſius</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering in time to <hi>Mulmutius</hi> and <hi>Mercia,</hi> and by the Lawes of <hi>Kennethus,</hi> not much diſtant from <hi>Alfred,</hi> and laſt of all by their Bookes of <hi>Regiam Maiestatem</hi> a principal booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, agreeing in effect with our <hi>Glanuill.</hi> And to ſay truth there was litle difference in Lawes and Religion, betwixt theſe two Nations, vntill the bloody warres, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan after the time of our King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, before whoſe daies <hi>Glanuill</hi> did write. Againe the moſt auncient of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Princes, &amp; law-makers, doe make mencion of many thinges in our common Law, which we are forced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that they receiued from the <hi>Britaines;</hi> for that, they ſpeake of them, as of things vſual and common, <hi>Ina, Alfred,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamb. Arc.</note> 
                  <hi>Edgar</hi> &amp; other the <hi>Saxon</hi> law makers, ſpeake of the Parlament, of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, of Treaſon, of Sanctuaries, of Purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of execution by hanging, for theft, of freſh ſute af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theiues &amp; homicides, of eſcapes, of Tearmes kept at London, of Recoueries, of Exchanges,<note place="margin">Hiſtoria Elienſis.</note> of Feoffements, of jntales, of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, incloſures, and the Law of <hi>Curia Claudenda,</hi> of the lawe of
<pb facs="tcp:17021:39"/>
diſceit, it in ſelling thinges corrupt or vitious; of dowers, Leaſes, Rents, Farmes, ſeruices &amp;c. And many other, as things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vſe, which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed as agreeable to Gods word, by thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being vtter enemies to the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> and yet moſt deuout in Religion, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in Iuſtice, as their Lawes doe teſtifie. For which cauſe I will touch certaine of the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Saxon</hi> lawes, onely to ſhew the Godlineſſe of thoſe auncient <hi>Saxons</hi> and Scottiſh Kings, and how in that time the matters of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawes were vſuall and common.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inas</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 720. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth his lawes thus: <hi>Inas</hi> by the grace of God, weſt <hi>Saxon</hi> King, by the perſwaſion and inſtruction of <hi>Cenred</hi> my Father, and of <hi>Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> and <hi>Erkenwald</hi> my Biſhops, and with al my Aldermen, &amp; the eldeſt wiſemen of my people, &amp; in a great ſummons of Gods Seruants, for the health of our ſoule &amp; conſeruation of our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (I haue enacted) that right Lawes and Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be confirmed throughout our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Cap. 1. That the miniſters of God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the appointed rules and maners of liuing: Then followeth Lawes for obſeruation of the Sabaoth, againſt theft, robbery, murder, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:17021:39"/>
other offences; and therein, is mencion alſo made of Land-lords, of Tennants, of Rents, and ſeruices. <hi>Kennethus</hi> the moſt worthy Scottiſh King, ſoone after the ſame time, maketh verye iuſt and good Lawes, wherof this was one. In e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Shire (this was before <hi>Alfred</hi>) Let skilfull men in the Lawes bee appointed to reſide, hee that blaſphemeth the name of God, of the Saints, of his Prince, or of the Captaine of his tribe, let his tongue bee cut out. The moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious K. <hi>Alfred</hi> about the yeare 880. beginneth his lawes thus: The Lord ſpake vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> theſe words, ſaying: <hi>I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the land of Egipt, out of the houſe of Bondage, thou shalt haue none other Gods beſides mee.</hi> And ſo foorth as in the deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log and other Iudicialles of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Then follow certaine lawes againſt periury, concerning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayles, againſt Sacriledge, Treaſon, Quarrelling, Fighting, Fornication, yea &amp; againſt immodeſt touching of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; with other lawes of greate ſinceritie, a manifeſt and approued Vicar and Lieuftenant of God, a ſecond <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is in the Lawe of the Lord, which to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, the ſame King tranſlated the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of Latin into the Vulgar Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the
<pb facs="tcp:17021:40"/>
vſe of his ſubiects, ſome Copies whereof (as it is ſaid) are yet remaining amongſt vs. So farre did the learning of thoſe daies differ from the ignorance of theſe <hi>Romane</hi> innouators. <hi>Edward Anno Dom.</hi> 920. Thus beginneth: I <hi>Edward</hi> K. commaund all <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeues</hi> that they giue right iudgements to all according to their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Booke. <hi>Alfred</hi> and <hi>Guthrun</hi> thus made their league by act of Parlament <hi>Ante omnia Deum vnum &amp;c.</hi> before al things that one God is to be loued &amp; Worſhipped. Secondly that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes are to be proclaimed as common to Chriſt and the King. Then followe Lawes for payment of Tithes, for obſeruation of the Sabaothes &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ioh. Picus cited by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lamb. Arc.</note> And by this league <hi>Guthrunus</hi> which ſome call <hi>Gurmundus,</hi> &amp; was in Baptiſme named <hi>Ethelſtane,</hi> obteyned <hi>Suffolke, Norfolke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Northumberland,</hi> to be giuen to him to holde by Fealty of the King. <hi>Edmund</hi> ſets this preface to his Lawes: I <hi>Edmund</hi> King to al my Subiects doe plainely ſignifie, that in a ſolemne aſſembly both of the Clergie and Laity, I haue ſtudiouſly inquired of the wiſeſt of my kingdome, by what meanes the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith might be moſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And to vs all it ſeemed moſt comodious that loue and mutual kindnes ſhould be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned
<pb facs="tcp:17021:40"/>
amongſt all men throughout our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Etenim tae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>et nos harum quotidianarum pugnarum,</hi> For we are tired with theſe quotidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an fightings and contentions. O godly Prince! O true Vicar of the God of Peace! <hi>Edgar</hi> enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Lawes for the obſeruation of the Sunday, and of publike feaſts and faſts vnder the paines contained in the iudiciall booke. And that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man ſhall freely enioy the benefit of the common Law. Note the common lawe euen then named, before S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> &amp; the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. <hi>Canutus</hi> the Dane thus: Firſt let all men moſt deuoutly &amp; religiouſly worſhip one God. Al men obſerue one rule of Chriſtian Religion. Al men obey <hi>Canutus</hi> the King with due fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and obſeruance. All defend and keepe the church of Chriſt with holy &amp; euerlaſting peace, &amp; continually freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame &amp;c, with many other moſt Godly and Chriſtian lawes, &amp; after many Footeſteps of auncient Lawes, which yet remaine in vſe, he concludeth with a moſte ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent exhortation to all men to turne vnto God and to obey his commaundements, another Lieftenant or vicegerent of Chriſt. <hi>Edgar</hi> the peaceable confirmeth the Liberties &amp; rights of the Church, &amp; amongſt other things, enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:17021:41"/>
that euerie man ſhall enioy the benefit of the common Lawe. Like matters are found in the Lawes of <hi>Ethelstane, Etheldred,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Conqueror, who confirmeth the ſame with ſome ſmall addition, and hath left them to vs conſecrated by his owne othe, and the othe of all his ſucceſſors. You ſee then the ſacred Maieſtie of our Imperaill Princes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath vouchſafed not onely by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſon of ſtrangers &amp; enemies, but by theſe their Lawes to be his Vicars &amp; defenders of his faith. And by theſe things that haue been ſaid, it may fully appeare, firſt how ſincerely and deuoutlye thoſe excellent Princes followed the counſell of <hi>Elutherius</hi> giuen to <hi>Lucius,</hi> in taking lawes for their kingdome out of the word of God, and how true it is that we affirme that our auncient common lawes were begun in the times of the firſt <hi>Britains,</hi> grounded vpon the lawes of God, printed in Nature and Scripture, continued by the <hi>Saxons</hi> in their iudgement bookes, &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to vs by Saint <hi>Edward</hi> and the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. And conſequently the ground of Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcues</hi> teſtimony, that this land hath bene poſſeſſed by <hi>Britannes, Romanes, Saxons, Danes</hi> and <hi>Normans:</hi> And in all the times of theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
<pb facs="tcp:17021:41"/>
Nations, and of their Kings, this Realme was ſtill ruled with the ſelfe ſame lawes and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, which if they had not bene right good, ſome of thoſe Kings mooued eyther with Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice or with reaſon, or affection, wold haue cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or aboliſhed them, ſpeciallye the <hi>Romane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who did iudge all the world by their owne Lawes. Thirdly what direction and Preſidents our Princes and Parlaments haue had to follow in making Lawes, and what Lawes the whole Kingdome is bound to obſerue, by that ſolemn othe that is taken for the obſeruation of St. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> lawes and the Lawes of the Realme, as partly alſo is noted vnto vs in the preface of that famous Statute, made againſt Prouiſors in the 25. yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third. And laſtly what reaſon may be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the manifold calamities, ſent by Almighty God, the moſt iuſt &amp; ſeuere judge at ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry times vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Realm, namely the ſuppreſsing, and conſequentlye the violation of this his Couenant, of theſe our auncient lawes, and of the law of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they are founded, by the predominant vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Idolatry, ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, iniuſtice, vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Breach of faith, and loialtye, both before the <hi>Norman</hi> and ſithence. If it be not ſo, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe
<pb facs="tcp:17021:42"/>
the Particulars that the holy <hi>Gildas,</hi> and aft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, the learned Sir <hi>Iohn Priſe</hi> obiecteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt <hi>Fritains;</hi> that the reuerend <hi>Bede</hi> and <hi>Geffery</hi> of <hi>Monmouth</hi> vrge againſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond age; that Maiſter <hi>Camden</hi> &amp; other Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, but ſpecially Maiſter <hi>Fox</hi> collecteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Saxons;</hi> that are at large deſcribed in the times of King <hi>Iohn</hi> &amp; King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, who ſuffered themſelues and theſe lawes to bee ouerſwaied by the ſupreheminence of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſide, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the beſt meanes to eſtabliſh the perpetuall vnitie and felicity of theſe two mightie nations, now againe reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we ſhall finde it to conſiſt principally in conforming them, both as much as may bee to the lawes, of that God of vnitie which ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the auncient Lawes of both kingdomes to be very like, &amp; almoſt the ſame, as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For what Kings haue reigned in more mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and glory then the Britaine Princes inſtiled by <hi>Elutherius,</hi> the Vicars of God in their kingdome, then the <hi>Saxon</hi> Princes indowed by <hi>Beda,</hi> with the Title of <hi>Chriſtianiſsimi,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Normans</hi> which haue moſte mainteyned theſe Lawes, &amp; moſt oppoſed themſelues againſt the vſurping power of the forraine Prelate, namely
<pb facs="tcp:17021:42"/>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. the 3. and the 6. <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. and the eight, acknowledged by the enemie of our faith to bee defender of the faith, &amp; the late moſt of all excellent, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which was bleſſed with a kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, longer then the raignes often that curſed her. And now the no leſſe excellent Maieſty of K. <hi>Iames,</hi> the true heyre aſwell of the goodneſſe as of the greatneſſe of his Predeceſſors. And who haue fallen into greater miſeries then thoſe that beeing inueſted with ſuch magnificent Titles by right, haue ſuffered others to take their Titles &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by vſurpation; of whoſe Calamities becauſe my heart doth tremble to thinke, I will forbeare my pen to write. Yet by this we ſee how God hath fed and directed vs with the ſtaffe of Beautie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.</note> and with the ſtaffe of Bandes, but now hee will breake his ſtaffe of beautie, to diſanull his couenant, made with all people, and hee will breake his ſtaffe of ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to diſſolue the Brotherhood between <hi>Iuda</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſraell</hi> except we repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our manifold ſinnes. I will therefore conclude with the Godly words of one of our famous and learned Iudges <hi>Bracton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bracto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. L. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> and one of our vertuous and Heroical Kings <hi>Canutus,</hi> The firſt taking his ground out of the many times remembred, and neuer to bee forgotten, Epiſtle of <hi>Elutherius,</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Rex non debet eſſe ſub homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſed ſub deo et Lege, ad ſimilitudinem Ieſu Chriſti,
<pb facs="tcp:17021:43"/>
cuius vices gerit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brvcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> li. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And againe Iudges doe ſit in the ſeate of the K. himſelf, as in the throane of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of the K. as inſteed of Ieſus Chriſt. For the K. is the Vicar &amp; Lieftenant of God, &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are not the iudgements of men, but of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid that the heart of the King is in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God. And a little after, into the ſeate therefore of judgement, which is as the Throne of the Diuine Maieſtie, let no man vnwiſe or vnlearned, preſume to aſcend, leaſt hee turne light into darkeneſſe, and darkeneſſe into light, and leaſt with an ignorant ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d like a mad man, he ſtrike the innocent &amp; ſpare the offender, and leaſt he fall from aboue as from the Tribunall of God, by attempting to flye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out winges to ſupport him. And when any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to judge, or to be made a judge, let him take heed, leſt by iudging peruerſly and againſt the Lawes, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt or reward, or a litle temporall comoditie, He purchaſe to himſelfe ſorrow &amp; griefe eternall: and leaſt in the daie of Gods wrath, he feele him to be a iuſt reuenger, who hath ſaid. To me vengeance &amp; I wil recompence, when the Kings &amp; Princes of the earth ſhal weepe &amp; lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the ſight of the Sonne of man, for the terror of his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, from which neither gold nor ſiluer can deliuer them. Who will not be affraid of that feareful trial, where the Lord himſelfe ſhall be accuſer, aduocate and iudge? from
<pb facs="tcp:17021:43"/>
whoſe ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeale. For the Father hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſon, who ſhutteth &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> openeth, &amp; openeth &amp; no man ſhutteth. O ſtrict &amp; ſeuere iudgment wherin me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal giue account not onely of their actions; but of euery idle word that they haue ſpoken! who ſhall eſcape from that ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to come? When the Sonne of man ſhal ſend his Angels, which ſhal gather out of Gods kingdom e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſcandal, &amp; thoſe that doe iniquitie, &amp; of them ſhall make faggots to burne and caſt them into the furnace of fire, where there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. Without queſtion God is a Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, and whoſoeuer taketh his Couenant, his oathe, his name in vaine, hee ſhall ſmart, for it he ſhall ſmart.<note place="margin">Lamb. Arc.</note> Now therefore ſaith <hi>Canutus</hi> in the concluſion of his Lawes; I beſeech all men in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and commaund euerie man in particular in the name of the immortall God that ſincerely, &amp; withall their hearts they turne to God, and withall care and diligence, ſearch what is to be done, and what it is to bee auoided (as it is a thing moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for our ſaluation) that we loue God &amp; keepe his commaundements, &amp; giue diligent heed to the words of his meſſengers For they ſhall produce vs before his ſight in the day, wherein the Lord ſhall come to iudge euery man according to his workes. Then happie ſhall that keeper bee, that ſhall bring
<pb facs="tcp:17021:44"/>
the flocke committed vnto him into the ioyes of heauen, by the paines that he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon earth, And bleſſed ſhall bee the flocke that followed ſuch a ſhephard which hath pulled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the pawes of the Deuill, and commended them as a purchaſe vnto God. Therefore let vs all in concord and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtuddie to pleaſe God, and fly from the fearefull torments of his wrath, &amp; iudgement. Let the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Miniſters of Gods word (as it is their charge and needefull to all mens ſaluation) often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times preach the glory &amp; ioyes of Gods kingdome, and let all men with diligent, ſerious, and attentiue eares and mindes, heare and obſerue them: yea let them beare the commaundements of God alwaies imprinted and infixed in their hearts. To conclude euerie man for the greater aduauncement of the diuine glorie, both in word and deed, Godly and cheerefully apply himſelfe to doe well, by what meanes ſoeuer they may. So at length in the end we all aboundantly ſhall obtaine his gracious mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Bleſſed be the name of the Lord, &amp; to him bee honor, praiſe, and glorie, from this time foorth for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <q>Deus non deſeret.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:17021:44"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
